<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Winter meditations directions how to employ the leisure of the winter for the glory of God : accompanied with reflections as well historical as theological, not only upon the circumstances of winter, but also upon the notable works of God, both in creation and Providence ... / by Cotton Mather ; with a preface of John Higginson.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24049</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07944491</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07944491</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40620</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40620)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1210:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Winter meditations directions how to employ the leisure of the winter for the glory of God : accompanied with reflections as well historical as theological, not only upon the circumstances of winter, but also upon the notable works of God, both in creation and Providence ... / by Cotton Mather ; with a preface of John Higginson.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
                  <author>Higginson, John, 1616-1708.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 82 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Benj. Harris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of (?) Cotton Mather</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Winter Meditations</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DIRECTIONS How to employ the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the WINTER For the Glory of God. Accompanied with Reflections, as well <hi>Hiſtorical,</hi> as <hi>Theological,</hi> not only upon the Circumſtances of the Winter, But alſo, upon the Notable Works of GOD, Both in, Creation, and Providence: Eſpecially thoſe, which more immediately Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern every Particular Man, in the whole courſe of his Life: And upon the Religious Works, wherewith e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man ſhould acknowledge GOD, in and from the Accidents of the WINTER.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Cotton Mather.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Preface of the Reverend, Mr. <hi>John Higginſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boſton</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>Benj. Harris,</hi> over-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Old-Meeting-Houſe.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:2"/>
            <head>To the Right VVorſhipful Sir JOHN HARTOP, Knight and Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen the Sons of the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> were Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling into that Country which was the <hi>Garden</hi> of the World, he ordered them, <hi>To take of the beſt of the Fruits of the Land, and carry a preſent unto a Great Perſon there.</hi> 'Tis into the <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of the <hi>European</hi> World, that a Little Book is now Travelling over the Atlantic Ocean;
<q>Hei mibi, quod Domino, non licet ire ſuo!</q> And tho' it carry not of the <hi>beſt of the Fruits of the Land;</hi> for it may without wrong to <hi>Me,</hi> be tokl you, that many parts of the <hi>Land</hi> afford far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; yet the <hi>Fruits</hi> which it carries, have this Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Recommend them, <hi>That they grew in the midſt of the barren Winter;</hi> but conſidering with my ſelf, to whom I ſhould make a <hi>preſent</hi> of theſe <hi>Fruits,</hi> the Character which YOU have among the Reformed Churches of God, a thouſand Leagues diſtant from the Iſland of your Abode, preſently determined this DEDICATION.</p>
            <p>Might we in this <hi>American</hi> Wilderneſs, more enjoy the <hi>Preſence,</hi> as I hope we cannot <hi>but</hi> enjoy
<pb facs="tcp:40620:3"/>the <hi>Good Will</hi> of perſons, like You, Accompliſhed, we ſhould have a Compenſation made us, for all the deſperate Hardſhip, of our <hi>Winters;</hi> but in the mean time we will Invite you to partake with us in our WINTER MEDITATIONS, when we cannot have you to partake with us in our <hi>Winter Difficulties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Altho' the <hi>Lines</hi> are fallen to You, in the <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Places,</hi> of a more Temperate Climate, yet the <hi>White</hi> Mantle of Snow at <hi>ſome Times</hi> covering that <hi>Happy Iſland</hi> alſo, beſpeaks for it the old Name of <hi>Albion;</hi> and if at <hi>ſuch Times,</hi> the Leſſons which then we have here had <hi>at our Fingers Ends,</hi> may give You as <hi>Acceptable</hi> an Entertainment as they would a <hi>Seaſonable</hi> One, my Satisfactions will even make me forget the Time of the Year.</p>
            <p>A moſt Excellent Pen, long ſince did publickly deſcribe You, as a Perſon, who were by Your Faith <hi>In Cacumine Olympi conſtitutus, ſupra Ventes et Proceſſas;</hi> above the <hi>Blaſts</hi> and <hi>Storms</hi> of this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet World. But. I perſwadè my ſelf, that a Treatiſe produced in the Months, that are full of Natural <hi>Blaſts</hi> and <hi>Storms,</hi> will have in it nothing Diſagreeable to that Serenity of Soul, wherein Your Faith has placed You.</p>
            <p>The Day comes on apace, when the World which was once <hi>Drowned, propter Ardorem Libidinis,</hi> will now be <hi>Burned, propter Teporem Charicatis.</hi> I have here made for a few of my Friends, an Eſſay, <hi>To fetch out one Cord by another;</hi> and albeit it would not be eaſie for to find <hi>All</hi> that ſhould <hi>Leſs Need</hi> the Admonitions of this
<pb facs="tcp:40620:3"/>
               <hi>Eſſay</hi> than You, yet, I believe, that <hi>Few</hi> will Receive it with ſo much Candor, Goodneſs, and Kind Reſentment.</p>
            <p>A Renowned Perſon once got himſelf an Immortal Sirname, only by an Invention, to come fairly at a Common Enemy, over and thorough Interpoſing <hi>Snow-drifts.</hi> I am here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to help my Neighbours with an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention how they may Encounter their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Enemies, the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> not only <hi>In,</hi> but even <hi>By,</hi> the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when God, <hi>Says to the Snow, Be thou upon upon the Earth.</hi> By this Undertaking, I have neither Purſued, nor Deſerved, any further <hi>Name</hi> for my ſelf; and yet I am upon this Occaſion ambitious, to Earn and Wear that <hi>Name</hi> of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sir, Your moſt Sincere and Very Humble Servant, <hi>COTTON MATHER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <p>IT is one of the Heavenly Counſels of Aged <hi>Pard</hi> to Young <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which reacheth to all Miniſters and Chriſtians in all Ages.</p>
            <p>[1 Tim. 4.7.] <hi>Exerciſe thy ſelf unto Godlineſs.</hi> Now that is done by a frequent practice of thoſe Duties, which have a Tendency to the promoting of the Power of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> in our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and which through the Bleſſing of God, will not fail to attain that End: amongſt which there are none more uſeful than <hi>Meditation, Self-Examination</hi> and <hi>Secret Prayer:</hi> Theſe are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Enjoyned by the <hi>Word,</hi> but Confirmed by the <hi>Experience</hi> of all the Saints, bearing witneſs to this great Truth, that there is no maintaining the Life and Power of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> without a diligent practice and frequent Exerciſe of the fore named Holy Duties; and therefore any Contribution of help towards any of theſe, and in particular that of <hi>Meditation,</hi> deſerveth a thankful acceptance from all the People of God.</p>
            <p>The Object of <hi>Meditation [God revealing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his Word and Works]</hi> is of a large Extent; the particularizing of ſome of the <hi>Works</hi> of God in <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence,</hi> conſidered
<pb facs="tcp:40620:4"/>with the adjunct of <hi>Time</hi> wherein they do Exiſt, and Expreſſing what the Word ſays of thoſe <hi>Works</hi> in their <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Seaſons,</hi> is of ſingular uſe to ſix the Volatile and Voluble Mind of Man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to profitable <hi>Medications</hi> with Application to our ſelves: as a Godly Man once ſaid, <hi>Shew me any C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cture, and I will ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w thee God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Works</hi> of God in their general Nature, and ſpecial kinds, are the proper Subject of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy; for <hi>Phyſica eſt Ars bene Naturan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di; Natura eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res nata e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>is: Principiuns eſt Materiale &amp; Formale; i.e.</hi> the Material and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Cauſes do conſtitute the Nature, and make up the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of every Creature of God in it ſelf conſidered: but the ſame Creatures &amp; Works conſidered in relation to the Supream Efficient and Final Cauſe, as they are from <hi>God</hi> as their <hi>Firſt Cauſe,</hi> and for <hi>God</hi> as their <hi>Laſt End,</hi> ſo they belong to <hi>Theology,</hi> and ſo the Holy Scripture doth abundantly treat of them, ſhewing Gods Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency running through, and influencing all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and Subordinate Cauſes, and entring into every Effect: and then the ſame Efficiency pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Being and Power of Working in all the Creatures, &amp; directing all their Motions thorough all &amp; above all their next interior <hi>Ends,</hi> to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as the laſt End of all; Hence every Creature hath its Exiſtence and Operations, as it is <hi>Ens a prime ad Primum;</hi> and thus the Holy Scriptures do every where proclaim God as the <hi>Firſt</hi> and the <hi>Laſt, Iſa.</hi> 44.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. in relation to all the Creatures; for <hi>of him, and through him, and to him
<pb facs="tcp:40620:5"/>are all things, unto whom be Glory for ever,</hi> Amen. Rom. 11.36.</p>
            <p>It is further obſervable, the Scripture doth not only treat of the Works of God themſelves, but of the Circumſtance of <hi>Time;</hi> not meerly as <hi>Time</hi> is <hi>Fluxus Nunc,</hi> or <hi>duratio rerum,</hi> but as its under a Divine Predetermination of the <hi>Seaſons</hi> of Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wherein every Creature doth Exiſt, and every Event ſhall come to paſs; and therefore it informs us, Acts 17.26. That, <hi>God hath determined the Times appointed before,</hi> and that, Eccleſ. 3.1. <hi>To e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing there is a Seaſon, and a time to every pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe under Heaven;</hi> and the Pſalmiſt ſpeaking to God, ſays, Pſal. 74.16, 17. <hi>Thou haſt made the Summer and the Winter, the Day is thine and the night alſo is thine:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> the Man of God tells us that <hi>Seed time, and Harveſt, Summer and Winter, and Day and Night ſhall not ceaſe,</hi> until the end of the World, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. <hi>laſt.</hi> In all which Expreſſions we are to underſtand, the Works of God that are done, and the Events of Providence that come to paſs in the <hi>Appointed Times and Seaſons of the Year;</hi> as now, In the <hi>Winter-time,</hi> Job 37.6, 7. <hi>God ſeals up the hand of every man, that all men may know his Work.</hi> In the <hi>Spring</hi> time he <hi>Renews the Face of the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 104.30. and revives all the Creatures. In the <hi>Summer</hi> time he <hi>Cloaths</hi> the Earth in its beſt Array, and gives the <hi>Fruitful Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; Mat.</hi> 6.30. Acts 14.17. and then in the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn</hi> he <hi>Crowns</hi> the Year <hi>with his Goodneſs,</hi> Pſal. 65.11. and brings in the <hi>Joy of the Harveſt,</hi> Iſa. 9.3. Nay the Pſalmiſt further informs us, that
<pb facs="tcp:40620:5"/>
               <hi>Day unto Day uttereth Speech, and Night unto Night ſheweth Knowledge,</hi> Pſal. 19.2. implying the various paſſages of Providence in every day and night of all the Seaſons of the Year, are ſuch as give Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to us in the Knowledg of the God who Made all, and Rules all, and will Judge us all at the Laſt Day, when all the Works of Creation &amp; Providence ſhall come to an end, &amp; when <hi>Time</hi> (that was Concreated with them) <hi>ſhall be no more:</hi> then God himſelf ſhall be <hi>all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28. World without End.</p>
            <p>Now in all the forementioned reſpects, this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pious and ingenious Treatiſe doth recommend it ſelf to every Intelligent Reader, as a ſingular &amp; ſeaſonable help to Improve the time of the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Seaſon in ſuch an Exerciſe of <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth us how to obſerve the <hi>Works</hi> of God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, &amp; to acknowledge God in them, &amp; by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Works</hi> of God together to have ſuitable (either ſett or occaſional) <hi>Meditations</hi> on the Wiſdom &amp; Power, the Greatneſs &amp; Goodneſs of God, and this with Application to our ſelves, and our own Duties, ſo as to raiſe our hearts and affections to the Fear and Love &amp; Service of that God, who is God <hi>over all bleſſed for ever more.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Ground I cannot forbear wiſhing that the Reverend <hi>Author</hi> of this, would do the like in relation to the other three Seaſons of the Year; being aſſured that the Holy Scriptures are as rich in furniſhing Materials for Spiritual Meditations on the <hi>Works of God</hi> proper to the <hi>Spring,</hi> the <hi>Summer</hi> and the <hi>Autumn,</hi> as well as to the <hi>Winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:6"/>
            <p>And truly, I cannot but give thanks to God, and Congratulate our <hi>New-England,</hi> that He hath Raiſed up ſuch a Learned, Pious, and Ingenuous Perſon amongſt the Miniſters of our Third Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and hath poured out his Spirit upon him, and hath Enabled him not only to an Exemplary Diligence in the Work of the Miniſtry both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly and privately amongſt his <hi>Own People</hi> with great Succeſs; but alſo to Write ſo many Uſeful <hi>Treatiſes</hi> on ſeveral Subjects, relating to the great Concernments of the Souls of all men, and of the State of Religion amongſt us at this day; which I doubt not but they have been, are and will be acceptable and profitable to the good people of this Generation, and thoſe that ſhall ſucceed.</p>
            <p>Finally, my hearts deſire and Prayer to God is; that he would graciouſly preſerve the Life and Health of this his Laborious and Faithful Servant, and give him to be <hi>Strong in the Grace that is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and Enable him to Write many more ſuch Uſeful treatiſes as he hath done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, for the Glory of God and good of the Souls of men, and that the Bleſſing of Heaven may go along with this preſent Work, and make it Effectual to attain the good Ends thereof.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Salem</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Higginſon</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:6"/>
            <head>THE Introduction</head>
            <p>IT is the Deſcription, which <hi>Martinius</hi> in that Noble and Learned piece of <hi>Geography,</hi> which he calls <hi>Atlas Chinenſis,</hi> gives con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Air in that part of the Eaſtern World, <hi>Majus in hac Provincia Frigus eſt, quam illius poſcat Pols Altitudo:</hi> Says he, <hi>The Cord in</hi> China, <hi>is greater than the Elevation of the</hi> Pole <hi>there would ſeem to allow: for the Country lies in little more than Forty Degrees of</hi> Latitude, <hi>and yet for four Months together in the Year, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers there are ſo Frozen, that the</hi> Ice <hi>will bear the paſſage not only of Men, but of Horſes and Coaches too, upon it. Yea, and the Ships are ſo ſhut up in their Harbours, that unto the beginning of</hi> March, <hi>there is hardly any ſtirring out; and there is more</hi> Froze <hi>in one day than there can be</hi> Thaw'd <hi>in many.</hi> I almoſt Thought that I read the Deſcription of our <hi>Winters</hi> in this part of our Weſtern World, in thoſe words of the Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher: for tho' the <hi>Latitude</hi> of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Town in this Province be but <hi>Forty Two Degrees, Twenty Seven Minutes,</hi> yet our Cold is by many Degrees more Fierce and Hard, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever more clear, pleaſant and wholſome than,
<pb facs="tcp:40620:7"/>that of many places that Ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beyond <hi>Fifty:</hi> and when it ſhall be told unto Strangers, that we have had <hi>Froſts</hi> both in <hi>June</hi> and in <hi>August,</hi> they will alſo conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, That our <hi>Winters</hi> muſt needs be as <hi>Long,</hi> as they are <hi>Cold.</hi> Now, the pinches of ſuch a <hi>New Engliſh Winter,</hi> Awakened me to Conſider, How ſo <hi>Cold</hi> and ſo <hi>Long</hi> a Time of Liverſion from very musk of our other Buſineſs, might be beſt Employ'd for the Glory of that God, who <hi>Made both the Summer and the Winter?</hi> As, 'Twas the manner of an Ingenious Perſon, when in the Morning there was a proſpect of a <hi>Fair Day,</hi> to ſay, <hi>'Tis pitty ſuch a Fair Day, ſhould be Loſt:</hi> ſo, The moſt of our <hi>Winter</hi> Days are <hi>Fair</hi> ones; not ſuch Dirty, Slappy, Low<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Thing, as fill the <hi>Winters,</hi> in ſome other Lands; and methoughts, 'Twas <hi>petty</hi> any of them ſhould be <hi>Loſt,</hi> as too many of them are. I am ſufficiently diſatisfyed at the ordinary Definition, which the Schools have given of the <hi>Cold, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Quality that Congregates Things both a like, and an un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e Nature.</hi> Yet I have been far more di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>isty'd, at the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o uſual way of ſpending our <hi>Dayes,</hi> when the <hi>Cold</hi> almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines us from our Chriſtian <hi>Congregations,</hi> But what ſeem'd the beſt way of Redeeming theſe <hi>Dares?</hi> Truly, I was willing to Try, not only whether there could not be found many pious <hi>Works</hi> to be attended with a ſingular convenience in the <hi>Winter,</hi> but a ſo, whether the Accidents of the <hi>VVinter</hi> is ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, might not afford ſomething to Aſſiſt us, and Quicken as, in thoſe <hi>VVorks.</hi> There are certain <hi>Flants,</hi> which keep <hi>Green,</hi> all the <hi>VVin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:40620:7"/>Long;</hi> and thought I, why ſhould not I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that the Exerciſes of Devotion, might ſo do, both in my-ſelf and others, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to be, <hi>As Green Olive-Trees in the Houſe of our God?</hi> The <hi>VVinter</hi> has been ſometimes called, <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ews <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ners,</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uggiſh</hi> Winter; but, I would contribute what I can, that it may be, <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Sancra,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pious</hi> Winter, the <hi>Holy</hi> Winter, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Winter; a <hi>Winter</hi> devoted unto the <hi>Works</hi> of the God of Heaven. To <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>p</hi> all <hi>Winter,</hi> more befits a <hi>Bear,</hi> than a <hi>Man,</hi> and much more than a <hi>Saint.</hi> It is very certain, That there is more <hi>Time</hi> contained in a <hi>Natural Day</hi> of the <hi>Winter,</hi> than there is in a <hi>Natural Day</hi> or the <hi>Summer:</hi> for, the Sun in its Animal Motion from the Weſt unto the Eaſt, thro' the <hi>Zodiac,</hi> paſſes equal Arches in unequal Times: the <hi>Winter</hi> Hall Year of the Suns paſſing from <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> to <hi>Aries</hi> is but an Hundred and Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a Fight Days, whereas the <hi>Summer</hi> Half Year of his paſſing from <hi>Aries</hi> to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bra,</hi> is no leſs than an Hundred and Eighty Seven Days: the Sun is Nine Days more in paſſing through the Semi-E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick of the <hi>Summer,</hi> than he is thro' that of the <hi>Winter;</hi> and accordingly an Hour upon the <hi>Sun D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> when the Sun is inclining to the <hi>VVinter-Tropick,</hi> is longer than an Hour upon the Dial, when he is advancing near the <hi>Summer Tropick.</hi> Hereupon, I could not but make that Reflection, <hi>If there be more, tho' it ſcarce be ſenſibly more, Time in a Day now, than at other Times in the Year, why ſhould I do leſs work for God, for Chriſt, for His Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now, than as other Times?</hi> and as an effect of
<pb facs="tcp:40620:8"/>that Reflection, Behold, Reader, ſome of my WINTER-MEDITATIONS.</p>
            <p>'Tis, as I remember, <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> who relates, that when <hi>Mathildis</hi> was, during the Depth of Winter, ſtraitly Beſieged, in <hi>Oxford,</hi> She arrayed her ſelf and her followers all in white, the colour of the <hi>Snow</hi> upon the Ground, and by the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of that Colour eſcaped thro' the Beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers unto a place of Safety. That which I deſire, is, a free paſſage for the <hi>Truths,</hi> and the <hi>VVays,</hi> and the <hi>VVorks</hi> of God, into the minds of my Neighbours; and I have therefore taken the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of putting a <hi>VVinter Complexion</hi> upon them; I have Clothed them in the Colours of the <hi>VVinter.</hi> And in this ESSAY, I have after a ſort Moralized the Fable of <hi>Antiphanes,</hi> That there is in a certain <hi>Scythian</hi> Region ſuch a <hi>Froſt,</hi> that the <hi>VVords</hi> uttered in the <hi>VVinter</hi> there Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gele ſo as to be not heard until the <hi>Summer</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhall diſſolve them: for 'twas at <hi>Boſton-Lecture,</hi> in the Month of <hi>December</hi> laſt, that the Heads of theſe <hi>VVinter-Meditations,</hi> were firſt <hi>Preached;</hi> and it is now in the Month of <hi>November</hi> following that they are <hi>Printed,</hi> on the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of <hi>Religion,</hi> that gave them their Original.</p>
            <p>When the Excellent <hi>Bartholinus,</hi> publiſhed his Book, <hi>De Uſu Nivis,</hi> it was accompany'd with an Epigram, ſomething to this purpoſe,
<q>
                  <l>Libros Authoris, quieun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> recenſet et Amos,</l>
                  <l>Amos quot poterit, tot Numerare Libros.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40620:8"/>
            <p>'Tis poſſible, that now I am Compoſing my Book about, <hi>The Uſe of the Winter,</hi> I may find my ſelf obliged to confeſs unto the World, as a Great <hi>Fault,</hi> what was indeed counted <hi>None</hi> at all in that Incomparable Perſon? I <hi>do</hi> confeſs, That I have written too many <hi>Books,</hi> for one of my ſmall Attainments; and I would ſay to my Reader, whom I now ſuppoſe by the <hi>Fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de,</hi> If this or any <hi>Book</hi> of mine, hinder men from acquainting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Bible, that <hi>Book</hi> of God, I wiſh, as <hi>Luther</hi> in that caſe did about his own <hi>Books, That they were all thrown into the Fire.</hi> But I hope, it will be otherwiſe; whereto I would alſo add, That all that <hi>Wearineſs of the Fleſh,</hi> as well as the various and humbling <hi>Temptation</hi> otherwiſe, which I have undergone, in the <hi>Study</hi> of, <hi>Writing many Books,</hi> has been abundantly Recompenced, by the comfort of thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, That the <hi>Free Grace</hi> of my Good God, will Accept of my poor Thoughts, to be Serviceable unto the Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts of His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World. And now I am Appendicing unto all the reſt, one <hi>Book</hi> upon the <hi>Winter,</hi> I will not ſay as my newly mentioned <hi>Bartholinus</hi> did in the Preface of his, <hi>Ego quidem ex hoc Niveo Labore, preter Atram Invidiam nihil Expecto,</hi> Or, That I expect nothing, but only to be <hi>Froſt-bitten</hi> with <hi>Envy</hi> for what I do. 'Tis true, There is a Froward Generation in every place, whoſe <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies</hi> muſt Perſecute all that Serve the Publick; and I have had the Experience of both my <hi>Fathers</hi> as well as my own, to convince me, that this place has of thoſe <hi>Frowards</hi> in it. If this People
<pb facs="tcp:40620:9"/>could have had <hi>Greater,</hi> which I know not, yet all mankind will ſhortly know, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any People to have <hi>Truer, Juſter,</hi> and more <hi>Indefatigable</hi> Servants, than ſome with whom I have the Honour to be well acquainted, have been to <hi>This:</hi> but the monſtrous <hi>Depreciations</hi> that have attended <hi>Them,</hi> have Taught <hi>Me,</hi> That I alſo muſt, <hi>Bene Agere, et Male Audire,</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, if I will Do <hi>VVell;</hi> and it will indeed be a life found, that unto all Activity in well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the Publick W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l, the <hi>Sport of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, is not a greater <hi>Freezer,</hi> than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Uſages. Nevertheleſs, I am ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as to think, That this is the Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of at leaſt, That there are multitudes among us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſo when any Servi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is done for <hi>them,</hi> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tlly give Thanks to God for <hi>it,</hi> and who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the <hi>Zeal</hi> with which they may ſee Almighty God inſpiring of any to be labouring for their Good. For the ſake of <hi>ſuch,</hi> none of our Thoughts, none of our Cares, none of our wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies, the too much; and it is unto <hi>ſuch,</hi> That <hi>Theſe</hi> of <hi>Mine</hi> are now humbly offered.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40620:9"/>
            <head>Winter-Meditations.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>It is Written in, JOB</hi> XXXVII.VI, VII.</bibl>
                  <p>He ſaith to the Snow, be thou upon the Earth; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the Small Rain, &amp; to the great Rain of His Strength.</p>
                  <p>He Seareth up the Hand of every Man, that all Men may know his Work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THat moſt Laborious and moſt Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Miniſter of the Goſpel, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had been Travelling on the Deſigns of the Goſpel all the <hi>Summer</hi> long, had ſome affairs of the Goſpel to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage in the <hi>Winter</hi> too. Speaking about a City of <hi>Thrace,</hi> he ſaid, in Tit. 3.12. <hi>I have determined there to winter:</hi> and accordingly in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, we find this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amous <hi>Doctor of the Gentiles</hi> once abode three <hi>months in Greece,</hi> after he had <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven much Exhortation</hi> to the People as he went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long. It ſeems the Service of the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40620:10"/>Chriſt, and of His Goſpel, was not in the <hi>Three Months of the Winter,</hi> to be laid aſide.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Us,</hi> we are now getting into our <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Quarters,</hi> and we ought not only to continue our Cares about <hi>Religion, &amp; Salvation</hi> and all the Works of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> all the <hi>VVinter</hi> long; but there are ſome ſingular Leſſons of the Goſpel to be in theſe <hi>Winter Months</hi> inculcated and entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Indeed, there is not <hi>One Day</hi> in the Year, whereon we ſhould not be, <hi>In the fear of the Lord all the Day long;</hi> but there are diverſe <hi>Months</hi> in the Year, wherein the <hi>Fear of God</hi> is to ſingle out ſome ſpecial ways of Exerciſe.</p>
            <p>That there are Special Duties of Chriſtianity, belonging to the <hi>winter,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intimated, in the words now Read unto us; and it is alſo intimated, <hi>what</hi> thoſe Chriſtian Duties are. Tis Piety that the <hi>winter</hi> ſhould advance any further upon us, before we have had ſome diſcourſe of theſe Duties: To be minding one another of theſe things, would be more Significant, and more Profitable, than our impertinent expence of time, in telling one another <hi>That it is very Cold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis poſſible that your Devotions here in this <hi>winter-ſeaſon,</hi> put you upon ſome Trial of your Patience. But I have an occaſion here to tell you; <hi>You have heard of the Patience of</hi> JOB. <hi>He</hi> was a Perſon of Quality, who dwelt in <hi>Arabia the Deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt,</hi> and yet that <hi>Arabia</hi> could not but be <hi>the Happy</hi> while it enjoyed the Preſence of ſuch a Ruler. But what a manifold <hi>Unhappineſs</hi> overtook this Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perſon, and <hi>Unhappineſs</hi> wherein he fell at once
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40620:10"/>from great Wealth and Health into Miſeries that have made a <hi>Proverb,</hi> all Ages have ſince heard, with wonderment. In theſe his Miſeries, he was viſited by ſome of his <hi>Comfortable Neighbours,</hi> who yet proved but <hi>Miſerable Comforters.</hi> Among theſe Viſitants there were <hi>Three</hi> more Aged <hi>Men of God,</hi> which Venerable Saints, all took their Turns, in dealing with him, about his Condition before the Lord; but at length it came to the Turn of a <hi>Fourth,</hi> who tho' he were a Younger Perſon, yet ſtood ſomething longer than the reſt in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Elihis,</hi> for <hi>That</hi> was his Name, is in our Context proving, That as there is a moſt Inſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Unblemiſhed <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> in all the Works of God, ſo in the Afflictions which the Lord had now ſent upon <hi>Job,</hi> there was nothing to be at all complained of. Whatever is done by our Great God, either <hi>in</hi> the Great World, or <hi>to</hi> the Little World, we have cauſe to ſay, <hi>He hath done ALL Things WELL:</hi> and there is no Work of God, whereof, all Circumſtances conſidered, we have not cauſe to own, <hi>His W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rk is perfect.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World could be more <hi>Arrogant</hi> than the Speech uttered by the King of <hi>Arrage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, That he could have contrived a better ſhaped World;</hi> nor more worthy to be Reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked with ſuch Burning Thunderbolts as the <hi>Spaniſh.</hi> Annals tell us, brought that haughty Monarch unto Repentance. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe <hi>Excellent Works,</hi> of the God who is, <hi>Excellent is working,</hi> ſuch Works as are every <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:40620:11"/>to be ſeen, have a Remark moſt particularly here ſet upon them.</p>
            <p>In our Text, Firſt, We have ſome <hi>Accidents</hi> of the <hi>Winter. He ſaith to the Snow, Be thou on the Earth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Small Rain, and is the Great Rain of His Strength.</hi> In the <hi>Winter,</hi> we have plenty of <hi>Snow</hi> and <hi>Rain;</hi> and thoſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Productions of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Kingdom,</hi> as the, come from the <hi>Word,</hi> ſo they ſhew forth the <hi>Strength</hi> of our God. Not only ſuch <hi>Snows</hi> as thoſe that fall upon <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> whereof ſuch is the Quantity, that <hi>Strabo</hi> tells us, whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of Men have periſhed, therein over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed: but the ordinary <hi>Snows</hi> of every <hi>Winter;</hi> Not only ſuch <hi>Rains</hi> as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that fall near <hi>Mexico,</hi> whereof <hi>Johnſton</hi> reports, that ſometimes the <hi>Drops</hi> are ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig and fierce as to kill the very people with their fury; but the ordinary <hi>Rains</hi> of every <hi>Winter;</hi> theſe have much of God, appealing in them. And one thing therein done by our God, is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[He ſeals up the Hand of every man]</hi> That is, By h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Weather he binds up their Hands, from doing any Work abroad. But indeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there are more than thoſe who work chiefly with their <hi>Hands,</hi> that feel theſe Obſtructions of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Wherefore the French Verſion ſo carrys it, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fait que chacun ſe Renferme;</hi> that is, <hi>Then he makes every man ſhut himſelf up;</hi> and it is very Expreſſive.</p>
            <p>There is an Impious Interpretation that ſome have made of theſe words; as if being, <hi>In m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40620:11"/>Omnium Hominum ſigna poſuit,</hi> they countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, <hi>Chiromancy;</hi> a fooliſh and abſurd Science, which pretends from the <hi>Lines</hi> in our <hi>Hands,</hi> to read the <hi>Fates</hi> of our <hi>Lives.</hi> As for that curious Vanity, I ſhall ſay but thus much of it; The <hi>Lines</hi> in our Hands, are moſtly formed, by the Accidental <hi>Uſes</hi> and <hi>Motions</hi> of our Hands; and may accordingly, by the like means be altered. <hi>Opinions</hi> about our future Circumſtances and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies, cannot be drawn to any purpoſe from theſe Lines, unleſs they be done mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe;</hi> and the <hi>Impulſe,</hi> which has often darted many true <hi>Predictions</hi> into the Minds of Ungodly <hi>Fortune tellers,</hi> when they have been po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing on the <hi>Hands</hi> of others, is ordinarily from ſome of the <hi>Demons,</hi> who are <hi>at Hand</hi> always to Encourage ſuch Impieties; and of the <hi>Predictions</hi> which the <hi>Demons</hi> have thus perhaps Litt upon, but as proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Conjectures,</hi> they immediately Employ all their Intereſt, which in <hi>This world</hi> is very great, for the Accompliſhment. Of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine Vengeance, leaving ſuch wretched <hi>Fortune tellers</hi> unto the more than ordinary power of the <hi>Devil,</hi> we have in our own I and, lately ſeen moſt horrid Inſtances. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way then, with all ſuch <hi>Diabolical Communions!</hi> Let us with a Chriſtian Reſignation, wait upon God, in a willing and a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ohome Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of, <hi>The Secret Things which being unto the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, Secondly, we have ſome <hi>Employments</hi> for the <hi>VVinter.</hi> Men are <hi>Seal'd,</hi> from their work when the <hi>Winter</hi> comes. But what? Have they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40620:12"/>
               <hi>no work</hi> then to mind? Yes; <hi>All men</hi> are then to <hi>know his work.</hi> To <hi>Know</hi> that work, is, according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort and Fulneſs of the Hebrew Phraſe to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> the work, to <hi>Love</hi> the work, to <hi>Do</hi> the Work. Why? The work is <hi>Gods work;</hi> the Work that God would have to he <hi>known,</hi> and therefore moſt worthy to be <hi>known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well; There is an Important CASE, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I would hence take occaſion to give you ſome WINTER ENTERTAINMENTS. It is The CASE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What Special</hi> Works <hi>for the Glory of God, may and ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the Children of Men, when by the hard we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her of the</hi> Winter, <hi>He ſhuts them up, or Hinders them from their Ordinary Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are not only <hi>Commoda,</hi> or Profitable Things, but alſo <hi>Accommoda,</hi> or Seaſonable Things which are to be Preached among you. Our <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is our <hi>Lieſure,</hi> and as it will be a <hi>Profitable,</hi> ſo 'tis but a <hi>Seaſonable</hi> Undertaking, to Lay before you, <hi>How the Lieſure of the Winter may be moſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for the Glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, without any further Preface, Firſt, that we may ſpeak more <hi>Negatively,</hi> it is to be aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. That the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>Winter</hi> muſt not be <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed,</hi> as if it were a <hi>Lieſure to work Abominations,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is were a <hi>Lieſure</hi> for any Superſtitious or Prohibited <hi>Senſualities,</hi> 'Tis not in the Slothful and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40620:12"/>Frothy Diverſions of <hi>Bad Company,</hi> nor in things which will <hi>wrong our Souls,</hi> that our <hi>Winter</hi> is to be Sweeled away. I am ſure, The <hi>Abominable Works</hi> of Sin, are none of thoſe <hi>works,</hi> which we are to mind, when God <hi>ſhuts</hi> up our <hi>Hands;</hi> No, we ſhould keep our own <hi>Hands</hi> for ever <hi>ſhut</hi> up from ſuch <hi>works</hi> as thoſe. Indeed, we ſpend the Nights of our <hi>Winter as a Tale that is told;</hi> but we ſhould not ſpend them in ſuch Idle Things, as the <hi>Telling of Tales;</hi> nor ſhould we give cauſe for a poor <hi>Tale</hi> to be told, about our way of ſpending them. Tho' our <hi>Winter-Days</hi> have not ſo much <hi>Light</hi> as <hi>Darkneſs</hi> in them, yet we ſhould all the <hi>Winter</hi> long behave our ſelves as <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light,</hi> and have <hi>no Fellowſhip with the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful Works of Darkneſs.</hi> 'Tis the Advice of the Apoſtle, in Rom. 13.12, 13, 14. <hi>The Night is far ſpent, the Day is at Hand; Let us walk Honeſtly, as in the Day; not in Dancing and Drunkenneſs; not in Chambering and Wantonneſs; not in Strife and Envying. But put you on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make not Proviſion for the Fleſh.</hi> Even thus, when the <hi>Nights</hi> come to be Longer than the <hi>Days;</hi> we ſhould ſtill do nothing but what the <hi>Day-light</hi> of the Goſpel Juſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines; 'tis not the <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>Luſt,</hi> or of <hi>Wrath,</hi> wherewith we are then to keep our ſelves in an <hi>Heat;</hi> whatever <hi>Winter Garments</hi> we get, we muſt not forget to <hi>Put on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that is, to have ſuch a Converſation as that every one who ſees us, may therein behold an Imitation of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; whatever <hi>Winter-Proviſions</hi> we Lay in, there muſt be no
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40620:13"/>
               <hi>Proviſions for the Fleſh,</hi> or Gratifications of our ſinful Appetires, among them all. Briefly, what is <hi>Honeſtly</hi> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ia'd in the Summer, muſt be but <hi>Soberly</hi> Spent in the Winter.</p>
            <p>There was one <hi>Winter Month</hi> in the Year, which was call'd <hi>Menſis Genialis,</hi> or the Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and Voluptuous <hi>Month,</hi> among the Ancient Pagans; it was the Month of DECEMBER, wherein the Heathen had their <hi>Saturnalian</hi> Jolli i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Then 'twas that they ſent their <hi>Preſents</hi> one unto another, which our Primitive Authors call by the Name of <hi>Saturnal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia,</hi> and by the Name of <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium Sportulae,</hi> but they alſo had monſtrous <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi> among them, whereto <hi>Horace</hi> refers, when he ſays, <hi>Age Libertate Decembri.</hi> None ſhall take Offence at me, for my giving of my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this matte; but I hope, I may without offence Report the Sentiments of the Great <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> who ſays, He did believe, that they who obſerved the feaſt of our <hi>Lords Nativity,</hi> in the latter end of <hi>December,</hi> did it not as thinking that our I o d was Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in that Month; but becauſe the <hi>Saturnalia</hi> were then kept in <hi>Rome,</hi> and they were willing to have thoſe <hi>Pagan</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lidaves Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſed into <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> And I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope, 'twill be no offence for me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e the Expreſſions of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Book againſt Idolatry, thus Expreſſeth himſelf; <hi>Shall we Chriſtians, who have nothing to do with the Feſtivals of the Jews, which were once of Divine h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion, Embrace the</hi> Saturnalla <hi>and the</hi> Januaria <hi>of the Heathen? How are we ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Gentiles, who are more true to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40620:13"/>than we are to ours? None of them will obſerve the Lords Day, Leſt they ſhould be Chriſtians; and ſhall n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we then, by obſerving their Feſtivalls, fear leſt we be made Ethnicks!</hi> Nor will I enter into any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, Whether the Birth of Our Lord were in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember;</hi> tho' they that are verſed in Antiquity, do underſtand how divided the Ancients were about it; and how late, yea, how many Hundreds of Years, it was e're the <hi>December Feſtival</hi> could obtain: and how much more probability there is, that it rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, about the time of the <hi>Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles,</hi> about the concluſion of <hi>September,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>October.</hi> But I will venture to ſay thus much, That it is well if the World be mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſince the famous and pious <hi>Biſhop</hi> made his Complaint <hi>That men diſhonour the Lord Jeſus Chriſt more in the Twelve Days of</hi> CHRISTMAS, <hi>than in an the Twelve Months of the Year beſide.</hi> And I will venture to ſay this more, That when the <hi>Corinthians</hi> pray'd the Apoſtle, to anſwer that Queſtion, <hi>Whether they might ſo be with, as to do like, the Pagans in thoſe Idolatrous Feſtivities?</hi> He plainly told them, <hi>No!</hi> Deterring of them, with the Example of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs, who would keep a <hi>Feast</hi> in Honour of the true God, but yet follow'd the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who in Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſaving them from Death by Expounding a Dream of <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> had a ſort of <hi>On-Worſhip</hi> among them: It is ſaid, <hi>The People ſat down to Eat and Drink, and Roſe up to play;</hi> and all the World has heard, what the <hi>Reckoning</hi> was!</p>
            <p>But if the miſpence of the <hi>Winter</hi> in Exceſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40620:14"/>of <hi>Eating</hi> and of <hi>Drinking,</hi> do deſerve a Caution, why ſhould not the <hi>Miſpence</hi> of the Winter in GAMING, do ſo too? Eſpecially the Games of <hi>pure L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> whereof thus much at leaſt may be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>That it is beſt for an Chriſtians to abſtain from them.</hi> Altho' moderate Recreations in the <hi>Winter,</hi> are more than a little <hi>Healthful</hi> and <hi>Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> yet there are ſome Recreations too much uſed in the <hi>Winter,</hi> which in Truth are never conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent; ſuch are the Games of CARDS, &amp; DICE, and thoſe which have nothing but CHANCE to manage them. A <hi>Lot</hi> is a ſolemn Appeal unto the God of Heaven; and hence to <hi>play</hi> with it, ſeems to break the Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Commandment in the Laws of our God. <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ry Lots</hi> are by Great and Grave Divines Eſteemed Unlawful, on the ſame Score that, as our worthy <hi>Morton,</hi> in his Rebuke to the <hi>Gaming Humour</hi> well Expreſſes it, <hi>It would be an Abomination unto any Chriſtian, to ſee a</hi> Pulpit, <hi>a</hi> Communion-Table, <hi>a</hi> Font, <hi>Expoſed on a Stage, or the Geſtures of Worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iped by</hi> Players. In eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> an Affair is wholly committed unto a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Cauſe than either <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Art,</hi> &amp; <hi>Skill;</hi> and this is a Thing to be done rather <hi>Prayerfully</hi> than <hi>Sportfully;</hi> even the Rudeſt Gentiles have counted a <hi>Lot, A Sacred Thing.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, will not allow of theſe Games in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Perſons; and the <hi>Fathers</hi> Reproved them with a vehement Zeal, in all manner of perſons. When the Roman Empire became <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſevere Edicts were made againſt theſe <hi>James;</hi> and what <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are we then that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40620:14"/>practiſe them. Our Proteſtant Reformers have branded theſe Games with an Infamous Character; yea, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſty</hi> the Orator himſelt, could produce it, as a Reproach unto ſome Ill men, that they were given to theſe Games. For which cauſe He that will follow, <hi>VVhatſoever Things are of Good Report,</hi> will not meddle with ſuch Infamous Things as theſe. In every <hi>Indenture</hi> for an Apprentice theſe words are uſual, <hi>At Cards, Dice, or any other Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful and Prohibited Games, he ſhall not Play.</hi> And ſhall we that are by <hi>Covenant,</hi> the Bound Servants of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, offer to Play at <hi>Games,</hi> that have been ſo Stigmatized? This however, you may be ſure of; There is a Truth in that Obſervation, <hi>That all the money got by theſe Games, is Like the Goods of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which Dy of the Plague, which commend, bring a Feſt with them.</hi> Nor is it altogether unworthy to be conſidered, <hi>That the more ſpecial Succeſſes of your T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rger Gameſters</hi>-(whereupon even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Themſelves do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times profanely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Devil will make a Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of that Young Man!</hi>) do very terribly intimate a peculiar Intereſt of the Devil in Ruling the Chance of theſe Games; 'tis an Obſervation which my moſt Honoured Friend, the Venerable <hi>Baxter,</hi> has made in the cloſe of his Book, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, <hi>The Worlds of Spirits.</hi> Pray then, have a care!</p>
            <p>And if men may Sin by ſome <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Gaming</hi> in the <hi>Winter,</hi> mayn't they do it in ſome kinds of READING too? Not only Books of Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jeſts</hi> and <hi>Songs,</hi> are very unworthy to be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40620:15"/>our WINTER-ENTERTAINMENTS, but the moſt of <hi>Romances</hi> too will then but create a <hi>Waſt of Time,</hi> to be Repented of. And here alſo, that I may not Impoſe my own Opinion, I ſhall give you the Judgment of two Writers, whom the World have not accounted Inconſiderable. The One is, The Author of, <hi>The whole Duty of Man;</hi> who Dehorting of Young Women from the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Romances,</hi> has theſe words, <hi>'Tis very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to Imagine what vaſt miſchief is done to the World by the falſe Notions and Images of things, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of Love and Honour, thoſe Nobler Concerns of Humane Life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſented in thoſe Mirrours.</hi> The other is, the Incomparable Dr. <hi>Tuckney;</hi> who likewiſe diſſwading of young Students from the Reading of <hi>Romances,</hi> has theſe words, <hi>Make this Trial, whether when you have been Greedy in Reading ſuch Books, you have thereby any great w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to Read the Bible. I am ſure that when you have been Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing That, you will have as little Delight i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reading them, as</hi> Paul <hi>had in the Thorn in his Fleſh, when he had been before caught up to Paradiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that I ſhall add, is, That when the Rules of <hi>Sobriety</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs</hi> are Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, Men inſtead of <hi>Knowing</hi> the <hi>Works</hi> of God, are <hi>Doing</hi> the <hi>Works</hi> of Gods Great Enemy; And I am ſure, The <hi>VVinter</hi> is not a <hi>Leiſure,</hi> for ſuch Odious <hi>VVorks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, <hi>Secondly;</hi> we may ſpeak more POSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIVELY; and it is to be now affirmed, That the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>Winter</hi> is to be Employ'd, in ſuch Things, as may be called, A WISE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEEMING
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40620:15"/>OF THE TIME. It is Enjoyned upon us, in <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>VValk circumſpecily, now as Fools, but as VViſe, Redeeming the Time becauſe the Days are Evil.</hi> Thus about the <hi>VVinter, Becauſe the Days are now ſhort and ſharp, therefore Let us now be ſo wiſe as to Redeem our Time in theſe Days.</hi> When we have <hi>Leaſt</hi> to do, we ſhould then be <hi>Beſt</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd. About the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>VVinter,</hi> we muſt own, <hi>Deus n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bis h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c Otia fecit;</hi> it is <hi>God</hi> that has made this <hi>Lieſure</hi> for us; and therefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us to Employ this <hi>Lieſure</hi> for God. We never have a <hi>Lieſure-Day</hi> befalling us, but we ſhould Eye the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>End</hi> of God, in order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a Day; and think with our ſelves; <hi>VVhy did my God ſend me this Day? what would He have me to do this Day?</hi> We are not <hi>VViſe,</hi> if on our <hi>VVinter-Days,</hi> all ſuch Thoughts as theſe Ly Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen in our Minds.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>How is VVinter-Time to be Redeemed?</hi> We will particularize.</p>
            <p n="1">I. In the <hi>VVinter</hi> we have <hi>Lieſure,</hi> to <hi>Reflect</hi> upon OUR OWN WORKS; and the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven does then Expect that we ſhould ſo <hi>Reflect.</hi> There are ſome, who take my Text in that ſenſe; <hi>He Seals up the Hand of every man, that every man may know his own work.</hi> We have Lieſure in the <hi>Winter</hi> to fettle our <hi>Iemperal Affairs,</hi> and we may then ſee whereabout our <hi>Work</hi> Lies; what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, what ſucceſs, we have had in our <hi>Work;</hi> and what further ſteps we are to take about our <hi>works</hi> The <hi>VVinter-time</hi> ſhould accordingly be a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40620:16"/>Time of much <hi>Contrivance</hi> with us, and a Time to State our whole Buſineſs, for all the Year a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. But more than ſo; our <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Affairs are thoſe which the <hi>Winter</hi> gives us the hoſt Lieſure for; and we ſhould now ſettle thoſe by Reflecting upon our <hi>work.</hi> It was complaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Jer. 8.6. <hi>No man Repented him, ſaying, what have I done?</hi> In the <hi>Winter</hi> we have Little to Do; well, but now 'tis a Time, for us to Reflect, <hi>What have I been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ever ſince I came into the World?</hi> The great work of <hi>Self-Examination</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods <hi>Work;</hi> 'tis the <hi>Work</hi> whereto our God has called us. We have a Precept ſo, it, in Hag. 1.5. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, conſider your W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> We have a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for it, in Pſal. 119.59. <hi>I thought on my Ways, and I turned my Fed unto thy Teſtimonies.</hi> VVe do the <hi>Work</hi> of God, when we thus <hi>Try</hi> what our own <hi>Works</hi> have been. VVhen the <hi>Winter</hi> then has driven us into Retirements, Let us take Time for this <hi>Work;</hi> even to <hi>See,</hi> and <hi>Know,</hi> what <hi>Work</hi> we have been doing ſince our God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt let us to <hi>work</hi> among the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing on the Earth. 'Tis now a Time for us to Enquire, <hi>How have I anſwered the End, which I came into the World upon?</hi> God has Required us, to <hi>work out our own Salvation;</hi> well, but what ſtrokes, have we ſtruck at that <hi>more</hi> all this while? Ask our ſelves, <hi>How have I done the works Agreeable to Repentance?</hi> and. <hi>How have I done the works of Believing on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> And herewithal bring we all our <hi>works</hi> to ſuch an <hi>Examination,</hi> as may diſcover
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40620:16"/>the <hi>Errors,</hi> and <hi>Follies</hi> of our <hi>Works,</hi> in order to our thorough Humiliation for them.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould not a <hi>Winter-day</hi> be ſometimes made a PRAYING-DAY, yea, and a FASTING-DAY, before the Lord? No man will arrive to very high Attainments in the Grace of God, who does not ſometimes, devote whole <hi>days</hi> unto a ſecret <hi>Communion</hi> with him. Now, let us have many ſuch Dayes every Winter, to <hi>Pray,</hi> and <hi>Faſt,</hi> and Humble our Souls, before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od of Heaven. But on ſuch a Day, one very proper exerciſe would be for us, to call over the <hi>Works</hi> of our lives, and finding the Obliquity of our <hi>Works</hi> by Comparing them with the <hi>Holy, &amp; Juſt, &amp; Good</hi> Commanements of our God, Let us then, <hi>Judg ourſelves that we may not be Judged of the Lord</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold a Catalogue of <hi>ſins,</hi> againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God; Reflect now diſtinctly &amp; exactly upon your <hi>works,</hi> and find out, whether you have not had ſuch <hi>ſins</hi> in your <hi>works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Demand of Yourſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>QUAESTION</hi> I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Have not I grievouſly <hi>forgotten</hi> the God that made me! And have not I given to the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the Homage which is due to God alone? Or, have not let Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have the <hi>Affection,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> which God alone may lay claim unto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt 2. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not Shamefully Neglected the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions</hi> wherein the Lord Jeſus Chriſt has taught me to mentain a <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with my God? and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40620:17"/>have I not humoured the <hi>Superſtitions</hi> of a <hi>Vain Converſation?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. | <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not Irreverently treated the <hi>Names, Attributes, Hords, Works,</hi> and <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi>whereby God makes Himſelf known unto us? and have I not been without awful Apprehenſions of His Majeſty, under His va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Diſpenſations?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not been Carnal, Careleſs, Weary in the <hi>Ordinary Sabbath</hi> of God? and have I not been Indiſpoſed unto the <hi>Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> Ones?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not been Perverſe and Haughty towards my <hi>Superiours?</hi> Unkind and Fooliſh towards my <hi>Interiours?</hi> Envious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my <hi>Equals?</hi> and miſerably <hi>Selfiſh</hi> in my conduct of my ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 6. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not Impaired my own <hi>Health</hi> by Intemperancies? or, been towards others, <hi>Paſſionate, Revengeful,</hi> and <hi>Contentious?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 7. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not been <hi>Unchaſt</hi> in my Acts, my Thoughts, my Words? Or, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en a <hi>Companion</hi> of the <hi>Fools</hi> that are ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 8. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not by <hi>Fraud</hi> nor <hi>Force</hi> wronged my Neighbour? Or, been too <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal,</hi> when I ſhould not have ſpent; but when I ſhould have ſpent, then too <hi>Niggard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 9. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not uttered, nor fomented what has been contrary unto <hi>Truth?</hi> or given Countenance unto a <hi>Falſe Report?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 10. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have I not been <hi>Diſcontent</hi> with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40620:17"/>my own Condition? Or, harboured in my Heart a Roving and a Craving <hi>Luſt,</hi> after an undue Alteration of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 11. <hi rend="margQuotes">Have not I Deſpiſed the Offers of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> and the wonderful provition therein made for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Sinners? And have not I permitted my Earthly Affairs to keep me at a Diſtance from the Lord-Redeemer, who has been waiting to give me, <hi>Repentance and Remiſſion of Sins?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 12. <hi rend="margQuotes">Is not the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all theſe bitten and curſed Streams, the <hi>Corrupt Nature,</hi> which I have Derived from my Firſt Parents? A Nature deprived of the Divine Image, depraved with abominable Inclinations?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon theſe Articles, Let us Interrogate our ſelves, concerning our <hi>Works;</hi> and thus in a <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> let us paſs a due <hi>Judgment</hi> upon our ſelves, for our own miſcarriages; that ſo we may in the <hi>End</hi> of the Year, make ready for the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> which is to come in the <hi>End</hi> of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Great God requires our <hi>Contemplation</hi> to obſerve ALL HIS WORKS, and the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>Winter</hi> ſhould very much go to that <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation.</hi> We ſhould now <hi>Know the Work of God,</hi> and Study as far as we can, every one of <hi>His Works.</hi> There has been that Invitation unto us, in Pſal. 46.8. <hi>Come, Behold the Works of the Lord, what Deſolations He hath made in the Earth.</hi> Truly, there are in every <hi>Winter,</hi> many <hi>Deſolations</hi> made upon the product of the <hi>Earth;</hi> but we ſhould then <hi>Behold All,</hi> as well as <hi>Thoſe works of God.</hi> We
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40620:18"/>are Endued with <hi>Rational Faculties,</hi> capable of <hi>Beholding</hi> the <hi>Works</hi> of our God; and He made us <hi>After</hi> all His other <hi>works,</hi> on purpoſe that we might be the <hi>Beholders</hi> of all the Reſt. Now, particularly</p>
            <p>Firſt, There is an Humble Acknowledgment of God, wherewith we are to <hi>behold</hi> his works of CREATION, and the <hi>winter</hi> may be our lieſure for it. The Pſalmiſt having mentioned the <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> when men lay by their labour, he preſently adds, in <hi>Pſal</hi> 104.24. <hi>O Lord how manifold are thy Works! in wiſdom haſt Thou made them all.</hi> As if <hi>then</hi> were a lieſure for ſuch a meditation! Truly thus in the <hi>winter,</hi> when we throw up our other Labour; we ſhould then, <hi>Behold theſe manifold works of God.</hi> We ſhould not in the <hi>winter</hi> become ſuch Recluſes as to forget that we are, <hi>The Citizens of the world;</hi> but then take a Range about the <hi>works</hi> of our God in the World. The very name of <hi>The World,</hi> in the Language of the Bible ſignifies <hi>Beautiful,</hi> and altho' in the <hi>winter</hi> it looſes much of its <hi>Beauty,</hi> yet we are then more at <hi>Lieſure</hi> to behold its <hi>Beauty.</hi> It was the Demand of the Pſalmiſt, in Pſal. 148.7.8. <hi>Praiſe the Lord, ye Hail, Snow, and Vapour, and Stormy wind: fulfilling his word.</hi> Why, <hi>The Snow, and Vapour, and ſtormy wind,</hi> and the reſt of the Winter, do demand of us, to <hi>Praiſe the Lord,</hi> for what of, <hi>The Lord,</hi> is to be ſeen in them, and not in them alone, but in all other Creatures. It is a moſt Glorious Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Objects, which we have to <hi>behold</hi> on this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Terraqueous Globe,</hi> we are at preſent <hi>ſojourners.</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:40620:18"/>There, to paſs over the Numberleſs <hi>Foſſils</hi> in the Bowels of the Globe, which probably contains above Ten Thouſand Millions of Cubic German Leagues, with how many <hi>Animate Bodies</hi> are we Entertained? Of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> including <hi>Serpents,</hi> we may reckon about an Hundred and Fifty <hi>Species.</hi> The <hi>Volatils,</hi> or Birds, have been reckoned about Five Hundred; The <hi>Aquatils,</hi> or Fiſh, have alſo been reckoned about Five Hundred. The <hi>Shell-Fiſh</hi> more than as many more. The <hi>Vegetables</hi> or Plants, of our Univerſe have been counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Six Thouſand; and the <hi>Inſects,</hi> both Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial and Aquatil, more than Ten Thouſand. But there are many other <hi>Animals</hi> to be alſo Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by us, which never could have been Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, until <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. Inſtruments were Invented for the doing of it. The <hi>Whales,</hi> thoſe moving Iſlands of more than an Hundred Foot in Length, are not of a Structure ſo Exquiſite, ſo Stupendous, as thoſe <hi>Animals,</hi> whereof our Microſcopes infallibly aſſure us, that many Thouſands together would not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual the leaſt Grain of our common Sand. But yet our <hi>Erect Figure,</hi> inſtructs us to <hi>Raiſe</hi> our Looks, unto the <hi>Stars,</hi> among which, if we were Lodged we ſhould quite Looſe our Sight of this <hi>Globe;</hi> tho' it be above Twenty Six Thouſand <hi>Italian</hi> Miles, in the compaſs of it. We have the faireſt and fulleſt view of the <hi>Stars</hi> in the <hi>Winter:</hi> (even the Cloud in <hi>Cancer,</hi> has been ſometimes then ſee, full of little Stars:) but what are thoſe <hi>Few,</hi> for they are not many more than a <hi>Thouſand,</hi> of the <hi>Stars,</hi> which we ſee without a <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40620:19"/>unto the Innumerable <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> wherewith from <hi>That,</hi> we juſtly ſuppoſe the <hi>Aether</hi> to be repleniſhed? The <hi>Wandring</hi> Stars, the <hi>Fixed</hi> Stars, and the <hi>Satellites</hi> of each, how inexplicably cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtanced are they? How Regular to the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredth part of a Minute, are they in their Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? and how more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulky than our Earth, an hundred times over, in their Dimenſions? If at laſt we Deſcend into the <hi>Sun,</hi> that vaſt Fiery <hi>Globe,</hi> which is the <hi>Center,</hi> and the <hi>Support,</hi> of the whole Viſible World Beſides; The Philoſopher thought himſelf Made and Born for nothing ſo much, as to Behold this Heavenly <hi>Fire ball:</hi> 'tis by the Ancient, and Sobereſt Computation, at leaſt an hundred &amp; ſixty times bigger than <hi>That</hi> Planer, whereof <hi>we</hi> are the Inhabitants: whereas indeed ſuch more Accurate Aſtronomers, as the Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Heveli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> have a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lerred the <hi>Sun</hi> to be three thouſand, four hundred and ſixty two times big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than this <hi>Earth,</hi> which is <hi>given to the Children of Men;</hi> but how much does it then, <hi>Declare the Glory of God, and ſhew forth His Hand; work?</hi> Let the <hi>Winter,</hi> when we ſee leaſt of <hi>him,</hi> give us <hi>Lieſure</hi> to be moſt Apprehenſive of it.</p>
            <p>The Jews have a Fancy among them, That when the Almighty firſt beſpangled the <hi>Heavens</hi> with <hi>Stars,</hi> He left a Spot near the <hi>North Hole</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiſhed, and unfurniſhed, that ſo, if in after Ages any other ſhould be ſet up for a GOD, he might have this Trial made of them, <hi>Go, fill up if you can, that part of Heaven which is yet left imperfect!</hi> But indeed without any ſuch Suppoſitions, we may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40620:19"/>ſee enough in the Heavens, to proclaim this unto us, <hi>Lift up your Eyes on High, and Behold, who has Created theſe things? None but an Infinitely Glorious God, could be the Creator of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. There is a profound <hi>Adoration</hi> of God, wherewith we are to <hi>Behold</hi> His Works of REDEMPTION; and for this likewiſe we have the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>Winter.</hi> When our Lord was undergoing ſome of His Laſt <hi>Agonies,</hi> for the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> of Loſt Man, 'tis ſaid in Joh. 19.18. <hi>They made a Fire of Coals, for it was Cold, and they war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med themſelves.</hi> Accordingly, when we have a <hi>cold Winter</hi> upon us, Let us <hi>warm</hi> our Souls by thinking on what our Lord Endured in the latter end of the <hi>Winter</hi> for us. When we are in our <hi>Warm Houſes,</hi> O Behold, that <hi>Hot Love</hi> of our Lord unto our Souls, which tho' He Lay in a <hi>Winter night</hi> groveling on the <hi>cold</hi> Ground, yet made Him <hi>Sweat,</hi> yea, to Sweat Clotters or Globules of <hi>Flood,</hi> more terrible to Behold than thoſe <hi>Bloody Sweats,</hi> which <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> tells us, befel the people of the Eaſt, when their <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> had bitten them. When we are in our <hi>Warm Garments,</hi> O then Behold the <hi>Heat</hi> of our Lords <hi>Love,</hi> wherein He Hung <hi>Naked</hi> on the Croſs, in the <hi>Cold Air,</hi> for Six Hours together of a <hi>Winter-Day.</hi> The Unfathomable Myſteries of <hi>Redemption</hi> are the <hi>Raptures</hi> of the <hi>Angels,</hi> all the Year about; it is ſaid of thoſe <hi>Cherubims</hi> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about the <hi>Mercy-Seat,</hi> in 1 Pet. 1.12. <hi>Theſe Things they Deſire to Look into.</hi> Let us make the ſame Things <hi>our</hi> Study, eſpecially in that part of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40620:20"/>the Year, the <hi>Winter,</hi> when we have moſt of Lieſure for the Study. We find, in Eccl. 11.7. <hi>Truly the Light is ſweet, and a pleaſant thing it is for the Eyes to behold the Sun.</hi> Tho in our Winter we have leſs <hi>Light</hi> than at other Times, yet we may then have more Time to <hi>Behold the Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> and how <hi>pleaſant</hi> a Task ſhould we E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it! Let us now take a Time to Behold the Matchl is <hi>Glories</hi> of our Lord Redeemer; and hear that Call of God. <hi>Behold, the Lamb of God!</hi> There is a bright Conſtellation of <hi>Miracles</hi> that Unite in our Bleſſed Mediator, and glitter won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully; Let us now, Behold thoſe Miracles of <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh,</hi> and of that <hi>Child Born to us, that Sun given to us,</hi> who is the <hi>Everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that <hi>Man</hi> who is the <hi>Mighty God,</hi> and whoſe Name is therefore <hi>Wonderful.</hi> But now alſo let us take a Time to Behold the Glorious <hi>Methods</hi> of our Salvation by this Lord Redeemer. Behold the moſt admirable Contrivance of our Salvation, in the <hi>New-Covenant!</hi> It is <hi>wonderful,</hi> that God ſhould <hi>ſo Love the World as to give His only Begotten Son, that whoſoever Believeth in Him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</hi> It is <hi>wonderful,</hi> that the <hi>Only Begotten Son of God ſhould ever take on Him the Form of a Servant, that we might become the Children of God.</hi> It is <hi>wonderful,</hi> that <hi>He who knew no Sin, ſhould be made Sin for us, that we might be made the the Righteouſneſs of God in Him.</hi> The Wayes of the Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> in <hi>Applying</hi> the <hi>Redemption</hi> thus obtained for us, are yet further WONDERFUL. The MYSTICAL BODY of our Lord Jeſus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40620:20"/>Chriſt, with regard unto the manner and effect, of our being brought into an <hi>Union</hi> with Him we are told, <hi>It is fearfully and wonderfully made.</hi> Well, we ſhould now, Behold theſe <hi>Wonders,</hi> and continue to do ſo, till we have no more <hi>Winter,</hi> yea, till we have no more <hi>Spirit</hi> Left.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, There is an Hearty Admiration of God, wherewith we are to <hi>behold</hi> his works of PROVIDENCE; and for this alſo we have the <hi>Lieſure</hi> of the <hi>winter.</hi> It is noted concerning the <hi>Wheels of Providence,</hi> in Ezek. 10.12. <hi>The Wheels were full of Eyes.</hi> When the <hi>winter comes about,</hi> in the <hi>wheel</hi> of the year, we ſhould have our <hi>eyes open,</hi> and be <hi>full of eyes,</hi> to behold the motion of thoſe wondrous <hi>wheels.</hi> The Government of the World is maintained in the <hi>winter,</hi> as well as all the reſt of the year about; but we have in the Winter, more of Lieſure, to behold the Spotleſs and Exact Adminiſtration of that <hi>Government.</hi> We behold ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtorms in the Winter; but it is then alſo a time to behold the <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God, in managing all the <hi>Storms</hi> wherewithal the world is Ruffled, and cauſing them all to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient unto his own Deſigns and Intereſts. It is ſaid in Pſal. 107.43. <hi>Whoſo is wiſe, and will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the Loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi> There are Illuſtrious Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, wherein the Almighty God acts as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder</hi> unto the children of men; and we ſhall be <hi>very well Rewarded</hi> for all the Confinements of the <hi>Winter,</hi> if we take our Lieſure now to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40620:21"/>our ſelves with ſuch Diſpenſations: Our <hi>Confinement</hi> will become our <hi>Liberty!</hi> There are the Diſpenſations, of the Moſt High towards His <hi>People;</hi> His Protecting them, His Directing them, His increaſing them. When the Church of God, was Repreſented unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> as a <hi>Burning Buſh,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>He drew near to Behold the Sight.</hi> And when we are by our <hi>Fire-ſide</hi> in the Winter, we may have Liberty to behold that <hi>Burning Buſh.</hi> There are alſo the Diſpenſations of the Moſt High, towards His <hi>Enemies;</hi> His Confounding of then, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Deſtroying of them. The Winter was hardly out, when <hi>Iſrael Beheld the Great Work which the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d upon the Egyptians:</hi> And we may <hi>then</hi> alſo behold, how terribly <hi>Egyptians</hi> are puniſhed by the Hand of God. When our Lord had been Talking with His Diſciples, about thoſe performances of <hi>Providence,</hi> wherein the Scriptures had Received their Accompliſhment, they could ſay, in Luk. 24.32. <hi>Did not our Hearts then Burn within us?</hi> Why, when we are e'en ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ze with the Vapours of the Winter, the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of our Lord ſhould then be Talking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, about His Doing, in the World; The <hi>News</hi> of Great Occurrents are then to be Enquired af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not as by <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>henians,</hi> having only an It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of Nowlty to prompt thoſe Enquiries, but as by <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> inquiſitive after the <hi>Fulfilments of the Scriptures:</hi> and after the Illuſtrations of the Divine <hi>Attributes,</hi> in thoſe <hi>Fulfilments.</hi> Thus are we to Talk till our <hi>Hearts Burn</hi> within us. And hence alſo, <hi>Church-Hiſtory</hi> is a very ſuitable Study for the <hi>Winter;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40620:21"/>Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ologies,</hi> and the Lives of Eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the Stories of Eminent <hi>Reformations,</hi> Difficulties, and Deliverances attending the Church of God, are now very fitly Studied.</p>
            <p>Finally. As it was ſaid, in Job 37.14. <hi>Stand ſtill, and Conſider the wondrous works of God:</hi> When the <hi>Winter</hi> comes, we can't <hi>Go out</hi> as at other times; Well, ſince we muſt <hi>Sit ſtill,</hi> now let us more than ever, <hi>Conſider the Wondrous Works of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. In the very CONSTITUTION OF THE WINTER it ſelf, There are very ſenſible <hi>Works</hi> of God, and our God requires <hi>us</hi> to be very ſenſible of thoſe Notable <hi>Works.</hi> Almighty God new <hi>Seals</hi> up our <hi>Hands,</hi> that we may <hi>Know His Work.</hi> What <hi>Work?</hi> Why, that very <hi>Work</hi> of <hi>Scaling</hi> up our <hi>Hands;</hi> and that <hi>Work</hi> of ſending <hi>Snow,</hi> and <hi>Rain,</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> upon the <hi>Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, when the <hi>Winter</hi> comes, we muſt Acknowledge that it is from <hi>God.</hi> It is as we read, Pſal. 147.17. <hi>Gods C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and for that cauſe we may not call it <hi>Cruel C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> at leaſt it muſt be a cruel <hi>Catechroſis,</hi> by which we call it to? nothing done by God, ſhould be Eſteemed <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> Even ſo, 'tis <hi>Gods Water,</hi> the Almighty God is to be Reverenced as the Orderer of it all.</p>
            <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Winter</hi> now Rolled about? Then <hi>Know,</hi> That God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the MAKER of the <hi>Winter.</hi> 'Tis E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red, in Job 38.28, 29. <hi>Hath the Rain a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Out of whoſe Womb came the Ice? and the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40620:22"/>Hoary Froſt of Heaven, who hath Gendred it?</hi> So, when the <hi>Winter</hi> is upon us, we may Enquire, whence <hi>comes this Cold,</hi> and <hi>Snow, and Rain, and all the reſt?</hi> But we ſee them all fall from <hi>Heaven;</hi> &amp; unto the God of Heaven ſhould we aſcribe the making of all. As the Winter is of Gods <hi>Promiſe;</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Antediluvian</hi> World had any proper <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> or no, yet the Lord preſently after the Flood, engaged concerning our preſent World, <hi>Summer &amp; Winter ſhall not ceaſe:</hi> Thus, the <hi>Winter</hi> is of Gods <hi>Making</hi> too. The Numberleſs Number of <hi>Saline Particles,</hi> from whence at leaſt ſome circumſtances of the <hi>Winter</hi> do ariſe, do all of them ſay, <hi>Tis the Lord that has made us, and not we ourſelves.</hi> There ſeems to be a vaſt ſtore of <hi>Corpuſcles</hi> a little akin to <hi>Nitre,</hi> exhaled from the Terreſtrial Globe, and ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving about in ſundry parts of the <hi>Atmoſphere</hi> (of the Figure which <hi>Philoponus</hi> tells us, <hi>Democritus</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd unto Frigorifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Atoms) and theſe may not a little contribute unto many things that we feel in our cold. But ſtill, who made them all? And thus, not only thoſe mighty Rands of <hi>Ice</hi> (that <hi>Magnum Duramen Aquarum,</hi> as <hi>Lucretius</hi> calleth it,) Encountred by ſuch Navigators as <hi>Janus Munckius,</hi> who ſaw theſe Icy-Iſlands floating Twenty Fathom above Water; or as <hi>Baffin,</hi> who found ſome above Water, between two &amp; three Hundred foot High; or thoſe that ſometimes occur in the River of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nada,</hi> where Icy-Iſlands have been ſeen, computed Fourſcore Leagues in Length; but every little Ice-Cycle is the Workmanſhip of God.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:40620:22"/>
            <p>Again, <hi>Know,</hi> That God is the SENDER of the <hi>Winter.</hi> 'Tis affirmed, in Job 37.9, 10. <hi>Cold comes out of the North; by the Breath of God, Froſt is given, and the Breadth of the Waters is ſtraitned.</hi> When a <hi>Northern Winter</hi> is nipping of us, 'tis from an Edict of God, giving order for ſuch a Seaſon. It is <hi>God that ſends Rain</hi> (and the Reſt) <hi>upon the Earth.</hi> The <hi>Winteriſh Winds</hi> blow our <hi>Winter</hi> about our Ears; yea, but it is the <hi>Breath</hi> of God, that is the <hi>Firſt Mover</hi> of all. There is much Diſpute, what is the <hi>Primum Frigidum;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Air,</hi> or <hi>Water,</hi> or <hi>Earth,</hi> or <hi>Nitre,</hi> or what? And ſome will Diſpute whether there be any ſuch <hi>Thing</hi> at all, or no. For if the <hi>Coldneſs</hi> of any thing ſignifie no more, than its not having its Inſenſible Parts agitated ſo much as thoſe of our <hi>Senſories</hi> by which we judge of <hi>Tactile Quati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> then to make a thing become <hi>cold,</hi> there needs no more than that the Sun or Fire, or ſome other Agent, that more vehemently Agitated its parts before, do now ceaſe to do it. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Cold a <hi>poſitive</hi> Quality, (which I encline to think) or a <hi>privative,</hi> ſtill 'tis the Death of God that gives Riſe unto it. What the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſaid about the Servants under His Command, <hi>I ſay to one, Come, and he comes;</hi> thus the <hi>Winter;</hi> 'tis our Great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign who ſays to it, <hi>Come;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Winter comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more, <hi>Know,</hi> That God is the RULER of the <hi>Winter.</hi> This is intimated in Pſal. 74.17. <hi>Thou haſt ſet all the Borders of the Earth, thou haſt made Summer and Winter.</hi> So, It is God, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ets
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40620:23"/>
               <hi>Borders</hi> to the <hi>Winter</hi> upon the <hi>Earth.</hi> It is <hi>God</hi> who ſays to the <hi>Winter, Keep off till ſuch a Month.</hi> It is <hi>God,</hi> who ſays to the <hi>Winter, Go off at ſuch a Month.</hi> The <hi>Unlimitable Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> is He that <hi>Limits</hi> our <hi>Winter</hi> for us. The <hi>winds</hi> that Riſe in the <hi>winter</hi> are in His <hi>Fiſt,</hi> and as to the <hi>waves</hi> that are ſo often Cruſted in the <hi>winter,</hi> ſo to the <hi>winter</hi> it ſelf, He ſaith, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou go, and no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me add, The Obedience of the <hi>winter</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God, ſhould be conſidered by us, to ſhame our <hi>Diſobedience.</hi> If God ſay to the <hi>Snow,</hi> and the <hi>Rain,</hi> and the Like, <hi>Be thou upon the Earth,</hi> ſtraightway they are ſo. What Wretches then are we, that when this God ſhall ſay to us, <hi>Be thou upon thy Knees,</hi> or, <hi>Let thy Heart be in Heaven,</hi> we ſlight what He ſaith! We read in Pſal. 147.15. <hi>He ſendeth f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th his Commandment upon Earth, His Word Runneth very ſwiftly:</hi> and then comes, the <hi>Snow,</hi> the <hi>Froſt,</hi> the <hi>Ice,</hi> and the <hi>Cold.</hi> VVell, but it follows, <hi>He ſhewed His Word unto Jacob.</hi> And now, does <hi>Jacob</hi> yield as much Obedience unto the <hi>VVord</hi> of God, as the <hi>winter</hi> does? Alas, How Diſobedient are we! In the <hi>winter,</hi> the <hi>VVork of God</hi> is done by the <hi>winter</hi> it ſelf; but the <hi>VVord</hi> of God then preſcribes a further <hi>work</hi> unto us; and can it be ſaid, We <hi>run very ſwiftly about that work?</hi> No truly; our <hi>will</hi> to our <hi>work,</hi> ſeems Congeled as it were by an <hi>Eternal winter.</hi> Said the Pſalmiſt, in Pſal. 119.91. <hi>All are thy Servants.</hi> What a ſad world is this! Every thing Obeys the Great God, without any Contradiction, but only
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40620:23"/>MAN, and the DEVIL? methinks we ſhould be aſhamed of our Company in our <hi>Diſobedience!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that our <hi>Obedience</hi> unto God may be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, by the very <hi>Conſtitution of the winter,</hi> we ſhould do well, upon the ſeveral Things therein occurring, to make our <hi>Occaſional Reflections.</hi> We may <hi>Spiritualize</hi> the <hi>winter,</hi> and we may have ſuch Thoughts thereby Raiſed in our Minds, and ſuch <hi>Leſſons,</hi> and ſuch <hi>VViſhes,</hi> as may bring unto us the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> which the <hi>Spiritually minded</hi> have in their being ſo. We will Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie a few of thoſe innumerable <hi>Devout Thoughts,</hi> wherein the <hi>winter</hi> ſometimes hath provoked a ſerious Man, to addreſs the God that made the <hi>winter:</hi> and I will confine my ſelf to the <hi>Scripture</hi> in them all.</p>
            <p>The firſt among all the <hi>Meteors</hi> of the <hi>winter,</hi> that uſes to be conſidered, is that of, The WIND, which <hi>Plato</hi> defines as well as any ſince, to be, <hi>The motion of the Air about the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſper ab Axe ruit</hi> Boreas, <hi>furit</hi> Eurus <hi>ab ortu,</hi> Auſter <hi>amat medium ſolem,</hi> Zephyruſque <hi>cadentem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Whatever Point of the Compaſs, the <hi>VVind</hi> blows upon, Let it blow ſome <hi>Good Thoughts</hi> into our Minds, and it will be no <hi>Ill VVind</hi> unto us. Now let theſe be the Withes of your Souls; Let this now be the <hi>ſtill voice</hi> of your Souls, and the <hi>Lord will be in the VVind.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Ezek. 37.19.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let the <hi>Breath come from the four winds, and breathe upon thy ſlain</hi> people eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, <hi>that they may Live.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Dan. 7.2.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let the <hi>ſtrivings of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40620:24"/>Wind upon the Sea,</hi> in the Tumults of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, produce the Accompliſhment of thy Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.36.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> bring not the <hi>four winds from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tors of Heaven,</hi> to ſcatter any part of thy Church <hi>toward all theſe winds.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Zech. 6.5.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me have many Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Kindneſſes done for me, by thine <hi>Angels,</hi> whom thou calleſt, <hi>The VVinds of the Heaven.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 27.8.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not thy Anger over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw me, but <hi>ſtay thy Rough wind in the Day of the Eaſt wind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 41.16. Iſa. 64.6.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not be found among thoſe, whom the <hi>VVind</hi> of thy Diſpleaſure ſhall <hi>carry away,</hi> and the <hi>VVhirlwind ſcatter them;</hi> and let it not be ſaid of me, <hi>My Iniquities, Like the VVind, have taken me away.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Job 20.15.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not thy <hi>Terrors,</hi> in ſore Calamities be <hi>turned upon me;</hi> Let them not <hi>pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e my Soul as the wind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 32.2. Pſal. 55.8.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let the Bleſſed JESUS, be unto me, <hi>As an Hiding Place from the wind, and a Covert from the Tempeſt;</hi> Unto Him, Thorough Him, <hi>Let me haſten my Eſcape, from the windy Storm and Tempeſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Matth. 7.25.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me be a <hi>Wiſe P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the <hi>Houſe</hi> of whoſe Faith and Hope ſhall be ſo <hi>Founded on the Rich,</hi> as to, ſtand, when the <hi>VVinds blow and beat</hi> upon it.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Hof. 13.15.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let no Adverſary like an <hi>Eaſt wind, come,</hi> and as the <hi>wind of the Lord, come up,</hi> againſt thy People.</q>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40620:24"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>[John 3.8]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> As <hi>the Wind Howeth where it Liſteth, and we hear the ſound thereof, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell whence it cometh, nor whither it goeth,</hi> ſo let me be <hi>Born of thy Holy Spirit.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Eccl 11.4.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not ſo <hi>obſerve the wind,</hi> as to neglect any Opportunities of <hi>Sowing,</hi> in Acts of <hi>Liberality.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Math 8.27]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> The <hi>Winds</hi> obey thy Chriſt; O Let <hi>me</hi> do ſo too!</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal. 18.10]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Unto the Saving and Helping of all thy people, do thou <hi>Fly upon the VVing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Wind;</hi> and let me do ſo, in the <hi>Swiftneſs</hi> of my Obedience unto thy Majeſty.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Gen. 8.1.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let that <hi>Wind paſs over Earth,</hi> which may carry off the <hi>Flood</hi> of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Wickedneſs and Miſery, that has Long Overwhelmed it.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jon. 4.8.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Expoſe me not unto any ſuch <hi>vehement Eaſt-wind</hi> of Calamity as may cauſe my Soul to faint.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[<hi>Act</hi> 27.7.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not have cauſe to complain, concerning my Voyage to Glory. <hi>The VVind would not ſuffer me</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal. 107.25, 29.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not a <hi>Stormy-wind be Raiſed</hi> in my Soul, but do thou make the <hi>Storm a Calm.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Eph. 4 14.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not be like a <hi>Child</hi> in Religion, <hi>Toſſed to and fro,</hi> and <hi>carried about with every wind of Doctrine.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jam. 1.6.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me alwayes <hi>Pray in Faith,</hi> not <hi>wavering like a Wave of the Sea, driven with the VVind.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40620:25"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jam. 3.4.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me will m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tage the <hi>Helm</hi> of my <hi>Tongue,</hi> when the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> winds</hi> are <hi>driving</hi> of me.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Job 7.7]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> cauſe me duely to <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that my Life is wind;</hi> ſo Tranſitory, and Evaneſcent! I am <hi>as the VVind that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſeth away, and cometh not again.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa 45.29]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Leave me not unto a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage upon thoſe <hi>Idols,</hi> which are but <hi>VVind and Confuſion.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Hoſ 8.7]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not fall into thoſe Iniquities, wherein I ſhall only <hi>Sow the VVind, and Reap the VVhirlwind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Job 15.2. Job 16.3.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not purſue that vain knowledge, which does but <hi>fill the Belly with the Eaſt-wind:</hi> nor let me uſe <hi>VVords of VVind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jer 5.13 &amp; 22.22. Eccl 5.5.16.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not my Expectations become <hi>wind;</hi> and let not the <hi>wind Eat up</hi> my Comforts: Nor let me in my Undertakings, <hi>Labour for the wind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Prov. 25.14.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not be a proud Boaſter of a <hi>Falſe Gift,</hi> like <hi>Clouds and VVind without Rain.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 7.2.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not be overcome with ſuch Fears, that my <hi>Heart ſhall be waved, as the Trees of the Wood, are moved with the Wind.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[So I Read, Cant. 4.16.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Depart O Northwind, and Come, thou South; blow upon my Garden, that the Spices thereof may flow out.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>The other <hi>Meteors</hi> that moſt abound in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40620:25"/>
               <hi>Winter,</hi> are the <hi>Aqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>nes,</hi> rather than the <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</hi> The whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeems to be a Great <hi>Vapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or <hi>Alemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for the Generating of them; their Origin is that in <hi>Pſal</hi> 135.7. and Jer. 10.13. <hi>God cauſes the Vapour to Aſcend from the Ends of the Earth.</hi> Well then, Of theſe. When the RAIN falls upon us by a <hi>Reſolution of Raiſed Vapours into drops of Water;</hi> Let our wiſhes be of this Import, and we ſhall have <hi>Showers of Bleſſing</hi> indeed; both in <hi>Summer</hi> and in <hi>Winter</hi> too.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal. 11.6. Gen. 19.24.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me be none of the <hi>Wicked,</hi> upon whom thou wilt <hi>Rain Snares, Fire and Brimſtone, and an Horrible Tempeſt,</hi> as thou didſt of old upon wicked <hi>Sodom.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jer. 17.6.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not my Soul be, Like the <hi>Heath in the Deſart,</hi> that <hi>ſees not when Good</hi> Rain <hi>cometh.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Acts 14.17.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me humbly Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Witneſs,</hi> which thou giveſt of thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Goodneſs, in thy <hi>Giving us Rain from Heaven.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Lev. 26.4 Deut 11.14. and 28.12. 1 King 8.36. Pſal. 68.9. and 65.11.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Evermore fulfil thy Promiſe to thy People, <hi>I will give you Rain in due Seaſon;</hi> and when they ask for it, Then <hi>Teach them the good way wherein they ſhould walk, and give Rain upon thy Land;</hi> and, <hi>Send plentiful Rains to confirm thine Inheritance when it ſhall be weary.</hi> So, <hi>Let thy Paths, the Clouds Drop Fatneſs upon us.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jer. 14: 22. ſee Zech: 10.1.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Are there any among the Vanities of the Gentiles, that can
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40620:26"/>cauſe Rain! Or, can the Heavens give ſhowers? Art not thou He, O Lord our God? Therefore we will wait upon thee; for thou haſt made all of theſe things.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Amos 4.7.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> I would own, That it is <hi>Thou who cauſeſt it to Rain upon one City, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt it not to Rain upon another City.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Mic. 5.7.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let the Accompliſhments of thy Word, unto thy Church, come, <hi>like the ſhowrs upon the Graſs, which tarries not for man nor waits for the Sons of men.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Math: 5.45.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> As <hi>Thou ſendeſt Rain upon the Juſt, and the Unjuſt,</hi> So let me do good unto all men, even unto my <hi>Foes,</hi> as well as unto my <hi>Friends.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Zech. 14.17. Iſa. 5.6.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not have a Soul, <hi>without the Rain</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>Joy,</hi> as they have, that come not into thy Church, to <hi>Worſhip</hi> the King, the Lord of Hoſts: Nor let thy Vineyard ſo offend thee, that thou ſhalt <hi>Command the Clouds to Rain no Rain upon it.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Deut. 32.2]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord, Let</hi> thy Word in the Diſpenſations of the Goſpel, <hi>Drop as the Rain upon my Soul.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal. 72.6]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let the Influences of thy Son the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>come down</hi> upon the World, and upon <hi>Me,</hi> in the World, <hi>Like Rain upon the Mown Graſs, as the ſhowers that water the Earth.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Heb. 6.7.8.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me not be <hi>Like the Earth, which Drinks in the Rain that comes oft
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40620:26"/>upon it, but bears Thorns and Briars, and is Rejected, and is nigh unto Curſing.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.12.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> It is <hi>Time</hi> for me <hi>to ſeek thee,</hi> that thou wouldeſt <hi>Rain down Righteouſneſs upon me.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 44.3.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> pour <hi>Floods</hi> of Celeſtial <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> upon my Thirſty Soul; pour and ſhower thy <hi>Spirit</hi> upon me.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[<hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.24]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not our Land, be a <hi>Land not Rained upon, in the Day of Indignation.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Job 5.9, 10]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Thou doſt <hi>Marvellous Things without Number,</hi> when <hi>thou giveſt Rain upon the Earth:</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 4.6.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> give me in thy ſelf a <hi>Place of Refuge and of Covert, from Storm, and from Rain.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal 84.6, 7]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Tho' <hi>the Rain fill the Pools,</hi> yet let me chearfully go thro' Wet and Dry, to wait upon thee in the Aſſemblies of thy <hi>Zion.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Gen 7.2]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Reſcue me and the World, from the Sins, that once provoked thee, to make it <hi>Rain upon the Earth, Forty Days and Forty Nights,</hi> till a Deſolating <hi>Flood</hi> came upon the World.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Ezr 10.9.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let a <hi>great Rain</hi> cauſe me to <hi>Tremble</hi> at thy greater Judgments.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Prov 27.15]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Send not upon me, an Affliction which may be as a <hi>continual Dropping in a very Rainy Day.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Prov 16.15]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let thy Favour in the Favour of my Rulers be to me, <hi>As a Cloud of the Latter Rain.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Hoſ 6.3]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord, Came unto me,</hi> in a way
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40620:27"/>of mercy, <hi>As the Rain, as the latter and the former Rain upon the Earth.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jer. 5.24.]</bibl> Finally <hi>Let me now fear the Lord my God, that giveth Rain.</hi>
               <p>Thus for the <hi>Rain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when the SNOW, which is Frothed <hi>Rain,</hi> lies about us, our Wiſhes may be thus Form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 55.10.11]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord, As the Snow comes down from Heaven, &amp; returns not thither, but waters the Earth, &amp; makes it bring forth &amp; bud,</hi> So let thy, <hi>Word accompliſh</hi> my being made fruitful before thee.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Prov. 25.13.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> As the <hi>Cold of Snow,</hi> (or drink Snow-Cold) <hi>in the time of Harveſt,</hi> is very acceptable, ſo let my <hi>Fidelity</hi> render <hi>Me</hi> to all that are concerned in me.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Job 19.30.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> help me to Conſider, that tho' <hi>I ſhould waſh my ſelf with Snow-Water,</hi> &amp; <hi>make my hands never ſo clean,</hi> yet much Filthineſs would cleave unto me, whereby I deſerve to be <hi>Abhorred.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Lam. 4.7.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> let a Work of real <hi>Sanctification</hi> upon me, render me like the <hi>Nazarites purer than Snow.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Numbers 12.10]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> make me penitently ſenſible of the <hi>Leproſy,</hi> upon my ſoul, which is a Diſtemper worſe than that Bodily one wherein, perſons have <hi>become</hi> Leprous, <hi>White as the Snow.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 1.18. Pſal. 51.7.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> let my <hi>ſins,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40620:27"/>that have been <hi>like Scarlet,</hi> become <hi>White like Snow,</hi> by thy Free and Full pardon of them all. <hi>O waſh me in thy Blood of Sprinkling, and I ſhall be whiter than Snow.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Dan. 7.9. Rev. 1.14]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> prepare me for, and haſten on the World, the coming of that <hi>Ancient of Days, whoſe Garments are white as the ſnow, and whoſe Hairs are white as Wool, as white as Snow.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Prov. 26.1]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> let me not be like one of thoſe <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls,</hi> for whom <hi>Honour would be unſeemly like the Snow in Summer.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Pſal 147.16 18.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> when thou haſt. <hi>given Snow like Wool, thou ſendeſt out thy word and melteſt it,</hi> and wilt not thou <hi>melt</hi> this heart of mine by thy word, into the Reſolutions of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Jer 18.14, 15]</bibl> 
               <hi>Will a man leave the Snow of, Lebanon, which comes from the Rock of the Fiel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Would a Thirſty Traveller, finding ſuch a Supply of pure water, ſlight it? Neither let me <hi>Forget thee,</hi> O my God.</q>
            <q>This for the <hi>Snow;</hi> But when the HAIL which is Frozen <hi>Rain,</hi> Viſits us, it may Awaken theſe Wiſhes in us.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Hag. 2.17]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> It was thy Complaint, <hi>I Smote you with Hail, yet ye turned not unto me;</hi> Let not my Obſtinacy in Sin, give cauſe for that Complaint.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Rev. 16.21.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Haſten upon the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian <hi>Babylon,</hi> that <hi>Great Hail out of Heaven, whereof every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tone ſhall be about the weight of a Talent.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40620:28"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa. 28.2]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not thy people be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded by any Enemy, which <hi>as a Tempeſt of Hail, and a Deſtroying Storm,</hi> ſhall <hi>caſt them down to the Earth.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[<hi>Ezek.</hi> 13 13. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.12.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let not my Refuges, be ſuch, as there ſhall be an <hi>Overflowing Shower in thine Anger, and Great Hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones in thy Fury to conſume them;</hi> Let them not be, <hi>Refuges of Lies,</hi> which <hi>the Hail ſhall ſweep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Fit me for the Day when I ſhall ſee the Deſcending Jeſus Alarum the World with <hi>Brightneſs, Hailſtones, and Coals of Fire.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Iſa 30.30.]</bibl> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me Tremble at thy <hi>Threatnings</hi> as they did in the Day, when thou didſt cauſe thy <hi>Glorious Voice to be heard,</hi> and <hi>Show the Lighting down of thy Arm, with Scattering, and Tempeſt, and Hailstones.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Joſh 10.11.]</bibl> Bleſſed be God, That He does not <hi>caſt down ſuch great Stones from Heaven upon us,</hi> as to make us <hi>Dy with the Hailſtones.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>[Exod. 9.20]</bibl> The <hi>Epyptians.</hi> being warned of a great <hi>Hail,</hi> ſuch as Feared the Word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> fled into Houſes for their Safety. <hi>Lord,</hi> Let me ſo <hi>Fear</hi> the <hi>Hailſtorm</hi> of thy Judgments, as to ſeek for Safety in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</q>
            <p>But it were Endleſs to Enumerate the <hi>Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of a Devout Mind, on theſe Occaſions. Thus, When 'tis FAIR, Clear, Bright WEATHER, how Agreeable were it for us to wiſh; <hi>Lord, may the Light of thy Countenance be Uplifted on my Soul!</hi> and, <hi>May I walk in that Light all the Day Long:</hi> So, when 'tis <hi>Cloudy Weather,</hi> how Agreeable to wiſh,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40620:28"/>
               <hi>Lord, When ſhall the Son of Man come in the Clouds of Heaven!</hi> and, <hi>O let it not be with my Soul, a Day of Clouds and of thick Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſhooting of ſuch <hi>Arrows</hi> up to Heaven, is an Incomparable Exerciſe for a Soul, that <hi>Looks</hi> to <hi>Eternal Inviſibles,</hi> to <hi>Inviſible Eternals,</hi> on a <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Day;</hi> and of the man, that on a <hi>Winter</hi> Day ſo Employs himſelf, I ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is the man, that has a Quiver full of ſuch Arrows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. The <hi>Merciful Words</hi> of God, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for our NECESSITIES IN THE WIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER are very manifold, and it becomes us to take a moſt <hi>Thankful Notice</hi> of thoſe many <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> When our God <hi>Seals up our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> in the Winter, He <hi>Opens His own Hand,</hi> in our Literal Supplies for the Winter; and we ſhould ſo <hi>Know thoſe Works of God,</hi> as to be Thankfully Affected with them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Winter</hi> it ſelf, <hi>That</hi> is not without much of <hi>Mercy</hi> in it. It is our <hi>Winter</hi> particularly, which for divers Months in the Year, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a better Defence unto us againſt Forreign <hi>Invaſions,</hi> than all the <hi>Sconces</hi> and <hi>Caſtles</hi> wherewith we could be Fortify'd. Doubtleſs the <hi>Polanders</hi> thought their Cold was a kindneſs unto them, when in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of ſeventy Thouſand <hi>Turks</hi> Invading them, Forty Thouſand ſuddenly periſhed, by the Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Cold, tho' it were but the Month of <hi>November</hi> with them. Truly, in the Month of <hi>November</hi> the Cold begins none of the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives alſo for us <hi>New-En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>anders!</hi> And who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40620:29"/>can ſay, How many <hi>Epidemical Diſeaſes</hi> have by our <hi>Winter</hi> been Extinguiſhed? Our Cold precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates the <hi>Vapours</hi> which would elſe Thicken and Poiſon our <hi>Air,</hi> and by Freezing the Surface of the <hi>Earth,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> keeps in many malignant <hi>Steams,</hi> that otherwiſe would thence ariſe to Suffocate us. It is called for, in Pſal 148.8 <hi>Praiſe the Lord, ye Hail, and Snow, and Vapour, and Stormy Wind.</hi> It ſeems, they that have <hi>much,</hi> of the <hi>Hail,</hi> the <hi>Snow,</hi> the <hi>Vapour,</hi> may find <hi>ſomething</hi> in them, for which they ſhould <hi>Praiſe the Lord.</hi> The Pſalmiſt ſays, <hi>God giveth Snow like W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l;</hi> the <hi>Snow,</hi> is as a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly white Robe on the Body of the Earth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is cheriſhed, with a <hi>Nitr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> Impregnation, for Fruitfulneſs in the Year Enſuing. <hi>Thuanns</hi> tells us, <hi>That ſometimes it has Rained Corn;</hi> and indeed, what <hi>Corn</hi> ſhould we have, if all <hi>Rain</hi> were deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto us? It was Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aculous, when God after a ſort <hi>Rained</hi> firſt <hi>Bread</hi> and then <hi>Fleſh,</hi> for <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old; He does it in Effect to: <hi>us</hi> continually.</p>
            <p>But as the <hi>Winter</hi> brings much of MERCY to us, it brings much of <hi>Hardſhip</hi> too? <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liny</hi> calls the <hi>Snow,</hi> and the <hi>Ice,</hi> the <hi>Puniſhments of the Mountains.</hi> We who dwell in a <hi>plain</hi> Region, as well as they who dwell upon the Rigid and Ragged Edges of ſuch <hi>Mountains,</hi> would be ſorely <hi>Puniſhed,</hi> by the Hardſhip of the Winter, if the Mercy of our God ſhould not Relieve us. It was ſaid, in Job 38.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2, 23. <hi>Haſt thou Entred into the Treaſures of the Snow? Or, haſt thou ſeen the Treaſures of the Hail? which I have Reſerved againſt the Time of Trouble.</hi> Truly, the Time of <hi>Snow,</hi> and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40620:29"/>Time of <hi>Hail,</hi> would be a ſore <hi>Time of Trouble</hi> unto us, if God ſhould not from the other <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> of his Bounty, therein make a Comfortable <hi>Proviſion</hi> for us. This I would ſay; The <hi>Common Mercies</hi> of God are a Ground, and call for more than <hi>Common Praiſes</hi> to God. May we from <hi>this Time,</hi> Reſolve to be more than <hi>ordinarily</hi> Thankful for our <hi>Common Mercies,</hi> and we have to Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Good Purpoſe now Spent the Time of this preſent Exerciſe.</p>
            <p>We may be Thankful, that the <hi>Winter</hi> it ſelf is not ſo <hi>Hard,</hi> either as it might be, if God ſhould make it ſo, or as it is now in ſome other Lands, yea, or as it has been heretofore among our ſelves. The Pſalmiſt ſaw cauſe to ſay, in Pſal. 147.17. <hi>Who can ſtand before His Cold?</hi> If God ſhould carry on the <hi>Cold</hi> unto a little further Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity upon us, there could be no <hi>Standing</hi> be ſore it. Or, if the <hi>Cold</hi> which in its Extremity tarries uſually but <hi>Three Days</hi> among us, were Extended for <hi>Three Mouths,</hi> inſtead of any <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> there could be no <hi>Living</hi> for us. But, in the midſt of the <hi>Cold, God Remembers Mercy.</hi> And <hi>Our Winters indeed are not ſo fiercely cold,</hi> as thoſe of ſome <hi>other Countreys.</hi> We are not, as <hi>Livy</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Alps, Eternis Damnati Nivibus,</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternal Snowes! 'Tis not with us, as <hi>Olearius</hi> tells us, tis in <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> where, Their <hi>Spittle</hi> will freeze e're it reach the Ground; and ſo violent is the <hi>Cold,</hi> that no Furs can hinder it, but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mens <hi>Noſes, Ears, Hands, and Feet,</hi> will be Frozen, and all fall off; And, as the Great <hi>Fletch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40620:30"/>has reported, not only they who Travel abroad, but many in the very Markers of their Towns are <hi>mortally</hi> pinch'd, ſo that you ſhall ſee many drop down in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; many Travellers brought home <hi>Dead</hi> and ſtiff in their Sleds. Which is a Report that <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>mundus ab Herberſtein</hi> has alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us Nor is it with us, as Capt. <hi>James</hi> found it, in ſome of his Northern Coaſting, where, when he and his Companions were a little while parted, they had their Face<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Hair, and Cloaths, frozen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that they could not know each other, by their <hi>Habits,</hi> no, nor by their <hi>Voices:</hi> Nor, as where <hi>Gerat de U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, when their <hi>ſhoes</hi> Froze as hard as Horns upon their Feet; nor were they able to wear them; Nor, as where <hi>Beauplan</hi> tells us, that without Good Precautions, the cold produces thoſe <hi>Cancers,</hi> which in a few Hours deſtroy the parts they ſieze upon.</p>
            <p>Yea, and our own <hi>Winters</hi> are, as obſervably as Comfortably Moderated ſince the I and has been <hi>Peopled,</hi> and <hi>Opened,</hi> of Later Years. Our <hi>Snows</hi> are not ſo Deep, and Long, ſince the Progreſs that has been made, in the Clearing of our <hi>Winds;</hi> and our <hi>Winds</hi> blow not ſuch Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs, as in the Days of our Fathers, when the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds of the Good Men would freeze unto the <hi>Bread</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Tables, and the ſtrongeſt <hi>Wine</hi> there would in a few minutes be hardly to be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for its Congelation: yea, <hi>Water</hi> caſt up into the <hi>Air,</hi> would be Turned into <hi>Ice</hi> e're it came unto the Ground. I wiſh, That all Wiſe Men would make the Reflection of <hi>Petronius</hi> upon
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40620:30"/>ſuch a matter; ſays he, <hi>Incultis Aſperiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tius Nives haerent: aſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aratro Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. Tellus nitet, dum Loqueris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evis pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ina dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitor: ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>iter in pectoribus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Conſidit; Feras quidem mentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>det, Eruditas praeterlabitur.</hi> In ſhort Engliſh: As our Land grows better <hi>Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated,</hi> we ſhall have leſs <hi>Winter</hi> and leſs <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> too among as.</p>
            <p>But then, Let our <hi>Thankful Thoughts</hi> proceed unto the more particular Proviſions, wherewith our kind God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>os us againſt the Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ults of a <hi>Needy Winter.</hi> Be thankful that we do not undergo the Torments of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>',</hi> in ſuch ſtarving Circumſtances, as Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory tells us, the Martyrdom of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> was attended with.</p>
            <p>Let us be Thankful for our CLOATHING It is a ſtroke in the picture of the wiſe VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>She is not Afraid of the Snow for her Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, for all her Houſhold are C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Garments.</hi> 'Tis well for us, that we have ſuch <hi>Garments</hi> by Night as well as by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, to keep off the Cold, which would otherwiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly mortify us. A poor Naked Beggar of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> being in the Depth of Winter asked by a Perſon of Quality, covered with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick Furrs, <hi>How be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ſo then clud, bear the Cold?</hi> He reply'd, <hi>My Lord, ſhould you do, as I do, you would feel as Little Cold as I!</hi> but being asked, <hi>How is that?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Why, As I do, Put on all the Clothes you've got.</hi> But indeed, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we were almoſt Naked, in the <hi>Cold</hi> of our Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40620:31"/>it would be but a <hi>cold Comfort</hi> unto us to think, <hi>Theſe few Thread-bare Clothes are all we have to Cover us.</hi> Be Thankful; and at the ſame time let us Entreat of our God, That He would beſtow upon us the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for the <hi>Garment</hi> of our Souls, and Adorn us with the <hi>Fine Linnen,</hi> which is <hi>The Righteouſneſs of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us alſo be Thankful for our FUEL. There have been <hi>Pagans</hi> that have ſometimes worſhipped the <hi>Fire</hi> as a <hi>God.</hi> But it would well become <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to Worſhip the True God with manifold Praiſes for the Advantages which we have againſt our Cold by the <hi>Fire.</hi> Our Indians have thought the <hi>Fire</hi> muſt needs be a <hi>God;</hi> becauſe when a poor man is ready to periſh with Cold in the Winter, one <hi>Spark</hi> of it, will in a few minutes blaze out ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably as to ſave the Life of him. Inſtead of ſo Rude a Fancy, it beſeems <hi>us</hi> to ſay, <hi>There is much of God in the Fire;</hi> His Greatneſs, and His Bounty may be ſeen <hi>Sparkling</hi> in it. Be Thankful; and at the ſame time, Let us En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of our God, That we may be <hi>Baptiſed</hi> with the <hi>Fire</hi> of His Holy Spirit, which will make us, <hi>Fervent in Spirit Serving the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us be thankful for Our HOUSES too. We are not left now to lodge abroad in the Cold, with none but the <hi>Ground</hi> for our Bed, the <hi>Snow</hi> for our Coverlid, and the <hi>Sky</hi> for our Canopy: nor are we obliged unto ſuch Wretched <hi>Wigwams</hi> as were the beſt Habitations of the Barbarous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40620:31"/>that were here before us. How well are we lodged in the Winter; and neither by <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> nor by <hi>Earthquakes,</hi> forced out of Doors? Be thankful; and at the ſame time let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of our God, that we have a <hi>Manſion</hi> in our Heavenly <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> forever. The Keeneſt <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in the world, have been made very tolerable by peoples making ſome Rooms of their Houſes under the <hi>Earth,</hi> and keeping themſelves in ſuch ſubterraneous <hi>Rooms.</hi> But let the <hi>Winters</hi> which call us to give thanks, for our warm <hi>Houſes</hi> on the <hi>Earth,</hi> cauſe us to be Concerned for, <hi>An houſe Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Heavens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us be Thankful for our TABLES. How many <hi>Warm Diſhes,</hi> have we to cheriſh us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are ſtrengthened againſt the <hi>Cold</hi> of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? And how many Refreſhing <hi>Draughts</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focillate our Enfeebled Spirits? Be thankful, &amp; entreat of God, that we may be admitted unto <hi>His Feaſt of Fat things full of Marrow, and of Wines on the Lees, well-Refined,</hi> the leaſt whereat, <hi>There will be no taking away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have a Glorious Benefactor in the Heavens by whoſe Benignity upon Earth, we live well all the Winter long: and all the Expreſſions of that Benignity, are to be Received with a moſt hearty <hi>Thankfulneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray, let us not be condemned, by the very <hi>Jewes</hi> themſelves, with whom it has been cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, ſtill to make uſe of their Daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, with a <hi>Baruk Adonai,</hi> or, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40620:32"/>
            <p>When <hi>Job</hi> was looking back upon the <hi>Good days</hi> which he had ſeen, he ſaid, in <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 29, 2.4. <hi>O that I were as in membe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as in the Days when God preſerved me; as I was in the dayes of my Youth!</hi> Some render it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>was in the days of my Winter Quarters.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, when the Great Commander of the Univerſe, does Command us into our <hi>VVinter Quarters;</hi> He do's then <hi>preſerve</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and by his <hi>Light</hi> we <hi>walk thro' the Darkneſs of the winter.</hi> And I would now ſay, <hi>O that we were ſo thankful, as we ſhould be for ſuch merciful months!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. The Works which, God his FORMER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY DONE TOWARDS OURSELVES, ought always to be <hi>Remembred</hi> with us; and the <hi>VVinter</hi> is a very proper Seaſon for that <hi>Remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is the <hi>werk of God,</hi> which we are to <hi>know</hi> when by the <hi>winter He ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ls up our Hand;</hi> even the whole <hi>VVork of God,</hi> in the whole courſe of our Life.</p>
            <p>There have been SMITING <hi>VVorks</hi> of God, which ought ſeriouſly to be <hi>Remembred</hi> with us; As it is ſaid, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 3.19.20. <hi>Remembring my Affliction and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the wormwood and the Gall, my ſoul hath them ſtill in Remembrance, and is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in me.</hi> Behold a fit <hi>work</hi> for the <hi>winter!</hi> Have we not ſometim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> been in a <hi>winter</hi> of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, wherein this and that <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> of <hi>Affliction</hi> and <hi>miſery,</hi> has been hard upon us? Now in the <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> let it be part of <hi>our work,</hi> to recount every ſuch <hi>work of God.</hi> Now bring to <hi>Remembrance</hi> all that <hi>VVormwood, and Gall;</hi> but what for?
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40620:32"/>Truly, to ſee whether you have been ſuch <hi>Gainers</hi> by all thoſe <hi>Chaſtiſements</hi> as you ſhould have been; and whether the <hi>weeds</hi> of the Corruptions in your Hearts, and of the Diſorders in your Lives, have been duely Nipt by the <hi>Freſt</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there have alſo been SMILING <hi>Works</hi> of God, which ought carefully to be <hi>Remembred</hi> with us. It was the Language of a <hi>David,</hi> in Pſal 103.2. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and forget not all his Benefits.</hi> To <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God,</hi> is not the leaſt of the Duties, which the <hi>Ever bleſſed God</hi> requires of man: and all true <hi>Davids</hi> or men <hi>Belov'd by God,</hi> ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <hi>Love</hi> to be <hi>Bleſſing of God.</hi> If this is to be done, <hi>At all times,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt elſwhere ſpeaks, I am ſure it may eminently be done in <hi>Winter-times.</hi> But God is not Really Bleſs'd or Serv'd, if not Heartily; and in our <hi>Bleſſing of God,</hi> the thing is <hi>Done to Halves,</hi> if the <hi>whole</hi> Soul, or all the Powers of the Soul, be not engaged in it. Indeed ſuch is our <hi>Backwardneſs,</hi> to the Bleſſing of God, that we had need earneſtly to ſtir, and ſpur, and rouſe our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto the Doing of it. Let us then <hi>ſtir up ourſelves,</hi> till we have got ourſelves into an <hi>heat,</hi> at this work, in our Winter, and know that a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration</hi> of <hi>Gods Benefits</hi> to us, is to be one Main Ingredient of Our <hi>Thankſgivings to Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then, Let this be one conſiderable Stroke of our <hi>Winter-work;</hi> even, To run over the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of our LIVES, by reckoning up the <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, and reflecting on that <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> wherewith we have been followed all our
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40620:33"/>
               <hi>Lives.</hi> What if you ſhould now and then ſpend whole DAYS OF THANKSGIVING, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when the Authority does uſually once in a <hi>Winter</hi> call the whole Province to obſerve ſuch a Day; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o in ſecret places before God, by yourſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Children of God, have doubtleſs Enjoyed, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon Earth,</hi> by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voting themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an Heavenly and Glorious Exerciſe; and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Devoted, has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with ſome obſervable Mercy of God. However, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> every <hi>Winter</hi> Set apart our Time, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the many <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and utter our Juſt <hi>Hallelujah,</hi> upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in that <hi>Commemoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Particularly; The FIRST Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the <hi>Protection</hi> which attended our FIRST PRODUCTION: Our <hi>Formation</hi> in the Womb, and <hi>Reception</hi> from the Womb. About our being <hi>Shaped</hi> in our Mothers, we may ſay, <hi>Lord, I wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> praiſe thee, for I am fearfully and wonderfully Made.</hi> And about our being <hi>Taken</hi> from our Mothers, we may ſay, <hi>Lord, Thou art He, who took me cut of the Womb.</hi> As for our <hi>Bodies,</hi> 'tis impoſsible for any thing to be better contrived, than they are in the whole <hi>Make</hi> of them. What a ſid thing would it have been, if theſe had been monſtrouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Deformed,</hi> or <hi>Defective</hi> in any One of all their <hi>Members?</hi> Truly, There are Thouſands of <hi>Mercies</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> in one <hi>perfect Child!</hi> And then, as for our <hi>Spirits,</hi> They are certainly the moſt <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:40620:33"/>Things that inhabit this Lower World. How doleful had been our plight, if theſe had Loſt any of their <hi>Faculties;</hi> were we <hi>Fools,</hi> or <hi>Mad?</hi> But indeed, we have Souls capable of a very vaſt Improvement, in the <hi>Honouring</hi> &amp; <hi>Enjoying</hi> of our God! What ſhall I ſay? That we are Arriv'd <hi>Alive</hi> among the Living on the Earth, is a Thing full of <hi>Marvels,</hi> if not of <hi>Miracles.</hi> What if we had Expired <hi>Embryo's,</hi> whereby all our Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities to Glorify God, had been Loſt for ever; yea, and this, after our being <hi>Animated,</hi> but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, before our being any way given unto God in the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> by our Parents; who 'tis poſſible were themſelves, <hi>At that Time Strangers from the Covenant of Promiſe,</hi> and ſo <hi>Having no Hope,</hi> for their miſerable Offſpring? O think on what thou <hi>Art,</hi> and what thou <hi>mighteſt</hi> have been! But,</p>
            <p>The SECOND Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the PLACE of our NATIVITY, or at leaſt of our HABITATION. Where do we <hi>Dwell!</hi> 'Tis in a Land, Enriched with all ſorts of <hi>Temporal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies.</hi> 'Tis not where we muſt have Endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>The Want of all Things;</hi> not in the <hi>Dark Places of the Earth, which are filled with Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</hi> We Dwell, where we have a plenty of <hi>Meat,</hi> of <hi>Drink,</hi> of <hi>Apparel,</hi> and of the Beſt; and it is plain, that the <hi>Poor</hi> do not in any Countrey Live ſo well as they do in <hi>Our's.</hi> We Dwell where we have the <hi>Right</hi> of ENGLISH-MEN for our <hi>Birthright;</hi> which is an <hi>Inheritance</hi> of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40620:34"/>more conſequence than what any other Nation upon Earth is favoured with: yea, and we have <hi>Additional Priviledges,</hi> as we are NEW-ENGLAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS, whereof we may ſay, as the Jewiſh Rabbi did of <hi>Liberty, If the Heavens were Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Seas were Ink, all would be too Little to write the Praiſes due unto our God upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</hi> We Dwell where <hi>Civility</hi> abounds; where <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> with <hi>Schools</hi> and other means for it, are promoted; where <hi>Vice</hi> is by wholeſome <hi>Laws</hi> reſtrained; where <hi>Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> is made Eaſie and Pleaſant by the Orders of it; and where <hi>Induſtry</hi> is Encouraged. But this is not all; <hi>Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Majora Canamus.</hi> 'Tis in a Land, Exalted with all ſorts of <hi>Spiritual Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;</hi> 'Tis not, where the <hi>People periſh,</hi> becauſe they <hi>have no Viſion.</hi> I pray mark it, It the world at this Day be Divided into <hi>One and Thirty</hi> parts, about <hi>Nineteen</hi> of them are Heathen Idolaters; about <hi>Seven</hi> of them are <hi>Mahometans;</hi> hardly <hi>Five</hi> of them are ſo much as called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And of what has been ſtyled <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> how ſmall a Moyeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, is reſcued either from that <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſtition,</hi> or <hi>Perſecution,</hi> which deſtroys all Real <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi> Yea, but you and I have, <hi>The Lines fallen to us in ſuch a pleaſant Place!</hi> We Dwell in a <hi>Goſhen,</hi> in a Proteſtant, and a Puritan Soyl; and where a Power to perſecute is by a Royal Charter for ever kept from coming into the Hands of any that might hereafter incline to uſe it on us. And, in what Age? Had we been Born a few Ages ago, it muſt have been in a <hi>Pagan,</hi> or in a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Age;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40620:34"/>and before PRINTING was Invented, when a <hi>Bible</hi> muſt have coſt a man an Incre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible Sum of money, if he could have got it ſo; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>Hanging</hi> or <hi>Burning</hi> into the Bargain. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, Brethren, There is not one of us, but what are Deſcended from the Loyns of many, that are now <hi>Roaring in the Place of Dragons!</hi> But as for us, we are Born in an Age of <hi>Light.</hi> Yea, 'Tis in the very <hi>Dawns</hi> of our Lords Coming to <hi>Deſtroy the Wicked One.</hi> I am verily perſwaded, There are ſome already <hi>Born,</hi> who ſhall ſee the moſt Glorious Revolutions that ever happened in any former Ages; even, <hi>The Glorious Things that are ſpoken of Thee, O thou City of God!</hi> It is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, To be Born ſo low, ſo far down in the <hi>Line of Time.</hi> To paſs on,</p>
            <p>The THIRD Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the FAMILY, which has given us our ORIGINAL, and our EDUCATION. What <hi>Parents</hi> have we had? perhaps we are not of the <hi>Houſe of the Wicked,</hi> which has the <hi>Curſe of God</hi> upon it; but in the <hi>Habitation of the Juſt,</hi> which is, <hi>Bleſſed</hi> by the Lord. We have had <hi>Parents,</hi> who have Pray'd for us, before they had us; as <hi>Abraham,</hi> as <hi>Hannah,</hi> did for theirs. Yea, perhaps upon their firſt Apprehenſions of our Conception, they did ſolemnly Give us up to God, that we might be for ever poſſeſſed by His Holy Spirit as the Everlaſting Veſſels of His Glory. But how much then have the <hi>Prayers</hi> of theſe our <hi>Parents</hi> been ſince concerned for us? And how Rich a <hi>Portion</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40620:35"/>have we had, in that <hi>Stock of Prayers?</hi> Little do Children think, what an Invaluable Bleſſing 'tis, to have <hi>Parents,</hi> that as <hi>Job,</hi> Sacrificed for his, <hi>according to the Number of them all,</hi> do pray for every one of them, and that by Name, every Day! But more than ſo; we have had <hi>Parents,</hi> that have <hi>Reſtrained</hi> us, when our Corrupt Natures would have been Exorbitant; nor Leaving us to be Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> with an Indulgence like that of <hi>Eli's.</hi> We have had <hi>Parents,</hi> that have <hi>Inſtructed</hi> us, and cauſed us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>come well Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed in the <hi>Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt;</hi> with a Diligence, like that of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Bat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> for their <hi>Solomon.</hi> We have had <hi>Parents,</hi> that have even, <hi>Travelled for us in Birth again, that Chriſt might be Formed in us.</hi> And what a Favour of Heaven, have we had in the Heavenly <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Parents!</hi> They have ſhown us, <hi>The Path of Life,</hi> by their own Walking in that <hi>Path,</hi> before our Eyes. Let us Imitate their Seriouſneſs, their Prayerfulneſs, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>fulneſs, their Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, their Watchfulneſs, and we ſhall at laſt, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſs, being therein <hi>Gathered unto our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> Whereas, moſt of the Children in the World, have <hi>Parents,</hi> by whoſe Influence they, <hi>Go to the Generation of their Fathers, where they ſhall never ſee Light</hi> Yea, 'tis poſſible, that we have had <hi>Parents,</hi> who have <hi>Liberally</hi> brought us up; by their Coſt and Care, we have been Educated in the <hi>Sciences,</hi> whereby we may be made ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>Serviceable</hi> to Mankind, ſingularly <hi>Honourable</hi> among our Neighbours. And I may add, That
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40620:35"/>ſome of us, who in our Childhood Loſt our <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> have yet found, that our God is the <hi>Father of the Fatherleſs:</hi> God has graciouſly ſtirr'd up <hi>others</hi> to do the part of <hi>Parents</hi> for us, when we were ſhiftleſs Orphans To proceed,</p>
            <p>The FOURTH Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the PROVISION which Divine <hi>Providence</hi> has made for us and ours. Our Lord ſaid once unto ſome of His Miniſters, <hi>When I ſent you without Purſe, Lacked ye any thing!</hi> And they ſaid, <hi>Nothing.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>we,</hi> whoſe <hi>Maintainance</hi> hath been Left unto the Arbitrary and Alterable Humours of a Fickle <hi>Multitude,</hi> and who perhaps have never made any Agreement with that <hi>Multitude</hi> about our <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> yet have hitherto been ſtrangely Supply'd in all our <hi>Straits.</hi> Many of our Neighbours, have but <hi>Impoveriſhed Themſelves,</hi> by not <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating unto their Teachers in all good Things;</hi> and if the <hi>Devils,</hi> who are the <hi>Rulers of this Dark World,</hi> could have had their Wills, we muſt have been Leggared, been Famiſhed. Yet we have ſeen, that we have Served a Good Lord: He has, as for the Tribe of <hi>Levi, Bleſſed our Subſtance;</hi> and He has been a <hi>Shepherd</hi> that would not ſuffer us His <hi>Under Shepherds</hi> to <hi>Want.</hi> But have not all our Faithful People alſo, had the like Experiences? <hi>Agurs</hi> Wiſh, has been granted us; even, <hi>Food con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for us.</hi> Yea, how many of us may ſay, That we never did properly <hi>Want,</hi> one good Meal, ever ſince we drew our firſt Breath? Speaking of our God, we may ſay with our Father <hi>Jacob, He
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40620:36"/>is the God, that has fed me all my Life Long, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Day.</hi> And what has been our <hi>Meat?</hi> our <hi>Drink?</hi> our <hi>Lodging?</hi> Have we not had for <hi>Delight,</hi> and <hi>Splendor,</hi> as well as for <hi>Neceſſity?</hi> It may be ſome of us, once had but very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the World; nevertheleſs as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Once I had no more than my Staff in my Hands, and now I am become two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> thus, when we began the World, we were hardly worth ſo much as the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Canes</hi> which we now carry in our Hands; whereas we are now Riſen to, how much of Grandeur! Thus have we been Supported. And, How <hi>Aſſiduo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly?</hi> We may ſay, <hi>The Lords Mercies are New every Morning.</hi> How <hi>Seaſonally?</hi> We have ſeen, <hi>When being Poor and Needy we have ſought Water, the Lord has given it.</hi> Indeed, our God has from Day to Day, carried us along as He did His <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs. We could ſcarce foreſee ſometimes one Day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, how we ſhould be Relieved for the Next; but our <hi>Heavenly Father</hi> has as well An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, as Understood, our Exigencies.</p>
            <p>To Go on,</p>
            <p>The FIFTH Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the FRIENDS, by the Beſtowal whereof, God Almighty has <hi>befriended</hi> us. VVhen men have been annoy'd by <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> it has been ſaid, <hi>God Raiſed them up thoſe Adverſaries.</hi> And ſhall not we that have ſuch <hi>Friends</hi> as we have, Acknowledge that they are of Gods <hi>Raiſing</hi> for us? But there are eſpecially our <hi>Friends</hi> of two Ranks, wherein we have been marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40620:36"/>favoured by the God <hi>who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tary in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies.</hi> Firſt, Our <hi>Conſorts.</hi> Have we not had ſuch WIVES, as may be truly called <hi>Good things,</hi> who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have obtained <hi>Favour from the</hi> Lord? 'Tis poſſible, we did in the Solemneſt manner, like <hi>Iſaac, As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> them of God, before we had them; and now tho' t'other Day, they were meer ſtrangers unto us, we do, as we have cauſe, value them above all the <hi>Relations</hi> that we have in the would beſides; and we do every Day that we live in the world, give our <hi>particular thanks</hi> to Heaven for our being ſo happily Accommodated. We have <hi>Conſorts,</hi> whoſe Good nature, whoſe Diſcretion, <hi>Doubles</hi> all our joys, and <hi>Halves</hi> all our Sorrows: <hi>Conſorts,</hi> who Live with us as the <hi>Heirs of Life,</hi> and give us a <hi>fit help,</hi> in our purſuing of that Inheritance; <hi>Conſorts,</hi> who are not a <hi>continual Dropping</hi> to us, as <hi>Jobs</hi> was to him, or as <hi>Abigails</hi> was to her. We had been the <hi>Undonneſt</hi> of men, if we had been ſo mated, as we have ſeen ſome, who have been thus <hi>undone,</hi> and could not <hi>undo</hi> what had in this thing been <hi>once done.</hi> And then Our <hi>Children.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>Lo, Children are an Heritage of the Lord.</hi> And how, Rich, have ſome of us, been in our <hi>Heritage! Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> we have had, that have been <hi>comely,</hi> that have been <hi>witty,</hi> that have been <hi>Well Diſpoſed.</hi> We have had <hi>Children,</hi> and God has not fulfilled His threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon us, <hi>Tho' they bring up Children, yet will I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave them. Ibzan</hi> the Judge of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> had thirty Sons, and thirty Daughters; and the Jews have a Tradition that he Buried them all, before he Died
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40620:37"/>himſelf: <hi>We</hi> have not been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bereaved.</hi> We have had <hi>Children,</hi> and they have not been like <hi>Eſau</hi>'s, <hi>A Grief of Mind unto us,</hi> but our Support, and our Glory. We may produce them, as the Roman Lady did <hi>Hers,</hi> for the moſt valuable of all our <hi>Jewels.</hi> To add,</p>
            <p>The SIXTH Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the <hi>Earthly</hi> VOCATIONS and EMPLOYMENTS, which <hi>Heaven</hi> has caſt upon us. 'Tis a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> to have a <hi>Calling.</hi> Tho' our <hi>Sweat</hi> be mentioned in our <hi>Curſe,</hi> yet our <hi>Curſe</hi> would be far greater than it is, if it were not for our <hi>Sweat</hi> 'Tis many wayes Advantageous, both for our inward and our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, that we ſhould, with <hi>Quietneſs work, &amp; Eat our own Bread.</hi> Let it be enquired of us, as it was of the Sons of <hi>Jacob, Of what Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are you?</hi> We have an Occupation; and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, it is not only a <hi>Lawful</hi> but a <hi>Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Occupation. It was the Benediction upon the Tribe of <hi>Judah, Let his Hands be ſufficient for him.</hi> Since we are of this <hi>Tribe,</hi> let us indeed be found in the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> or of <hi>Praiſing</hi> ones. But more than this; we have an <hi>Agreeable</hi> Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Tis no little kindneſs of our God unto us, when we come to love, to like, to chooſe our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Buſineſs;</hi> when our <hi>Buſineſs</hi> is made our <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and we do not come to it, as the Bear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtake. The Lord ſaid, <hi>Behold, I have cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the Smith, who blows the Coals in the Fire, and bringeth forth an Inſtrument for his Work.</hi> Thus 'tis God that <hi>Spirits</hi> one man for this Work, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40620:37"/>another man for that work; and when a mans Lot falls to him in that Work, whereto he has been particularly <hi>Spirited,</hi> this is the kind work of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And that which Augments this kindneſs of God, is, that we can ſo follow the <hi>work</hi> of our calling, as to mentain ourſelves, and yet we have Time to mind the affairs of our <hi>Souls</hi> too; we can without pinching, allow one whole Day in a week, for <hi>ſoul-work;</hi> and be at <hi>Lectures &amp; Meetings</hi> every week, for more of that <hi>work:</hi> &amp; every Day in our <hi>Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Cloſets,</hi> do ſomething further at that <hi>work;</hi> and ſo, <hi>Work out our own ſalvation.</hi> Yea, ſome of us, have an <hi>Honourable</hi> Vocation alſo: We have either in the <hi>Government,</hi> or in the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſuch a ſtation that many thouſands may fare the better for us! Theſe are thing that call for the moſt grateful Reſentments of our Souls. But then.</p>
            <p>The SEVENTH Article in our <hi>Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the Marvellous PRESERVATIONS which have been afforded us, by the Glorious <hi>Preſerver of men.</hi> Have not our Lives been fill'd with <hi>Preſervations,</hi> by Him that is, <hi>The Keeper of Iſrael?</hi> Yea, We have been preſerved from <hi>Sin.</hi> What if we had been Left unto our ſelves? We ſhould ſoon have been ſo many <hi>Devils Incarnate.</hi> When the Holy <hi>Bradford</hi> heard of any Wickedneſs committed in the Neighbourhood, he would ſay, <hi>Alas, In this Heart of mine, there is that which would cauſe me to commit the Like Wickedneſs, if God ſhould give me up to my own Heart.</hi> Thus, we may ſee prodigies
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40620:38"/>of Wickedneſs in the world; but we muſt aſcribe it unto the pure <hi>Grace</hi> of our God, that we alſo are not ſuch Ruined and Rueful Creatures. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, conſidering what Furious Aſſaults of <hi>Temptation</hi> have been made upon us: For it is indeed probable, that moſt of us, have at ſome times undergone more violent Aſſaults of <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> whereof we may ſay, <hi>My Feet were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well nigh ſlipt.</hi> Had not the Good God ſtrangely and ſtrongly, kept us back, at thoſe Times, we had undoubtedly caſt our ſelves over the moſt Irrecoverable <hi>Precipices;</hi> but here was the Goodneſs of God, who would not <hi>Suffer us to be Tempted above what we are Able:</hi> 'tis He that may now Remind us, <hi>I witheld the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from ſinning againſt me.</hi> And we have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from <hi>Sorrow</hi> too. We have had that word fulfilled unto us, <hi>The Lord ſhall preſerve thee from all Evil, the Lord ſhall preſerve thy going out, and thy coming in.</hi> Pauſe here, a little, I beſeech you; How many <hi>Sickneſſes</hi> have we Eſcaped? Either the <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> never touch'd us, or, like <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> we have been Reſtored from them. How many <hi>Caſualties,</hi> have we alſo E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded? Let the <hi>Traveller,</hi> Let the <hi>Marriner,</hi> Let the <hi>Souldier</hi> now Enumerate his Deliverances. One that Received a great <hi>Fall</hi> from an <hi>Horſe,</hi> but Received no <hi>Hurt</hi> by the <hi>Fall,</hi> ſaid of it, <hi>I never had ſuch a Deliverance in my Life;</hi> but one well Reply'd, <hi>Yea, Sir, you have, as often as you Rode without Falling at all.</hi> This I ſay, Our <hi>Deliverances</hi> have been far from Inconſiderable, even then,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40620:38"/>when we have not had Senſible and Imminent <hi>Hazards</hi> to ſignalize them unto our Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In a word, we have been ſurrounded with <hi>Evil Angels</hi> on every ſide of us, every day; and thoſe <hi>Divels</hi> have always been Watching, Wiſhing, Snatching, to <hi>Devour</hi> us. But our God has muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zled thoſe Hungry <hi>Lions;</hi> and has granted us a guard of <hi>Good Angels,</hi> whoſe <hi>Miniſtry</hi> has been uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to us, in many Thouſands of <hi>Good Offices,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we ſhall never be exactly advized, until we are Tranſlated into their <hi>Innumerable Company.</hi> And yet this is not all!</p>
            <p>The EIGHTH Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be the <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the Evident ANSWERS of our PRAYERS, by the Merciful Hearer of <hi>Prayer.</hi> May not you and I make this Relation, <hi>This poor man has cry'd unto the Lord, &amp; the Lord has heard and ſav'd!</hi> Cannot we lock upon one enjoyment, and ſay, <hi>This is a</hi> Naphtali, <hi>I wreſtled with my God for this, and ſo I obtained it!</hi> Can we not look upon another enjoyment, and ſay, <hi>This is a</hi> Samuel, <hi>I asked it of my God, and ſo I had it!</hi> When Diſtreſſes have been upon our ſelves, we have gone to our God, and having <hi>Offered up our Prayers and Supplications,</hi> we have <hi>been Heard in what we feared.</hi> And when diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have been upon others, perhaps we have like <hi>Abraham,</hi> like <hi>Moſes,</hi> like <hi>Samuel,</hi> and like <hi>David,</hi> and like <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> prevailed for the Remoual of them. A Miniſter of the Goſpel, 'tis probable may ſee the Faces of ſome Scores in his Congregation, of whom he may ſay, <hi>God gave that Soul from death
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40620:39"/>to my poor unworthy prayers!</hi> Yea, 'tis poſſible the very <hi>Divels</hi> have not been able to ſtand before our <hi>Prayers;</hi> our <hi>Prayers</hi> have perhaps more than <hi>thrice</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed the <hi>Devils,</hi> who had ſiezed upon ſome of our <hi>Afflicted</hi> Neighbours. Let me tell you; <hi>Pſalms to bring unto Remembrance,</hi> are to keep us from <hi>forgetting</hi> the Returns of our <hi>Prayers!</hi> But further yet;</p>
            <p>The NINTH Article in our <hi>Commemoration</hi> may be, The <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the <hi>Means</hi> of our SANCTIFICATION, and the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of thoſe <hi>Means.</hi> Let us now <hi>Declare</hi> unto ourſelves, and ſo make ourſelves Ready to <hi>Declare</hi> unto others, <hi>What the Lord has done for our Souls.</hi> That we have the Means of <hi>Grace,</hi> is a thing that lays us under Adamantin Obligations unto Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs. Have we, <hi>The Word, the Statutes, the Judgments,</hi> of God ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n unto us? What ſhould follow, but <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord!</hi> For indeed, He hath not <hi>ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> with every <hi>Nation.</hi> Yea, But has <hi>Grace</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo been convey'd unto us, by theſe means? His does make our Obligations unto Thankfulneſs to become truly infinite. Has the Great God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>Own Son</hi> to us, and for us, and with him <hi>Freely given all things?</hi> Are we Invited unto a <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who <hi>ſerves his</hi> People <hi>from their ſins?</hi> A <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who <hi>delivers from the wràth to come?</hi> A Chriſt, in whom there <hi>does all fitneſs ſwell?</hi> O our Hallelujahs, where are you? Indeed, we could never have come unto this Jeſus without the <hi>Drawing of the Father.</hi> But has he' <hi>drawn</hi> us? Has the Spirit of God made
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40620:39"/>it a <hi>Day of his Power</hi> with us, and have we been made willing, in that memorable <hi>Day?</hi> We were <hi>Dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins;</hi> Has the Spirit of God <hi>quickened</hi> us? We were <hi>Going aſtray in the greatneſs of our</hi> Folly; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit of God <hi>Reduced</hi> us? We have been <hi>Pining away in our Iniquities;</hi> Have we been Recovered by the Sanctifying, the Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening, the Comforting <hi>Spirit</hi> of our God? O the Matchleſs loving kindneſs! And, pray, what are the <hi>Means which God has deviſed,</hi> for the bringing back of our Souls, which have been <hi>Baniſhed</hi> from His <hi>Paradiſe?</hi> We have not only had the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of God, made uſeful unto us, for the <hi>changing</hi> of us into His <hi>Image,</hi> from <hi>Glory to Glory;</hi> but His <hi>Providences</hi> too. Even thoſe very <hi>Afflictions</hi> which have <hi>happened</hi> unto us, have not come only by <hi>Hap;</hi> there has been the Good <hi>Hand,</hi> and the Good <hi>End,</hi> of our God in all; and tho' we had been ready to ſay, <hi>All theſe things are againſt me,</hi> we now ſee, <hi>That all things have wrought together for our Good.</hi> We ſhall have cauſe to magnify the Name of our God forever, for the Reſtraints which he has laid upon us, by our <hi>Afflictions,</hi> and for the <hi>Right Thoughts,</hi> which our <hi>Sad hours</hi> have Raiſed in us. 'Tis by theſe <hi>Means,</hi> that <hi>we</hi> are now brought into the <hi>Covenant of Grace.</hi> And now, O moſt Highly Priviledged we! The <hi>Great</hi> God is become <hi>our God.</hi> God the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> is become our <hi>Father;</hi> God the <hi>Son,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our <hi>Saviour;</hi> God the <hi>Spirit,</hi> is become our <hi>Strengthener;</hi> All the <hi>Perfections</hi> of this God, are now concerned for our Welfare. We have now
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40620:40"/>a Title to all the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God; we may have a continual Recourſe to them, as unto our <hi>Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and the Rejoycing of our Heart;</hi> we may from them aſſure our ſelves of <hi>Grace,</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> of <hi>Every Good Thing.</hi> Our Spiritual <hi>Enemies</hi> will all be Diſappointed; we have an Omnipotent Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker for our being made <hi>Conquerours and more than Conquerours over them</hi> And whither are we now a going? Our Heavenly <hi>Shetherd</hi> is daily <hi>Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of us <hi>in the Paths of Righteouſneſs;</hi> but whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Truly, to another and a better World; Every Day we are one Day nearer to the <hi>Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in Light.</hi> We ſhall ſhortly, be with our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>VVhere He is, that we may Behold His Glory!</hi> But, <hi>O my God, How Long! How Long!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Are not here <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Commemoration</hi> enough to fill the Thoughts of one <hi>Winter Day?</hi> And yet, that the Muſick may not be Impair'd by our miſſing of any <hi>Note</hi> that may belong un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, annex a TENTH Article to all the Reſt. Let <hi>That</hi> be, upon the <hi>Benefits</hi> of God, relating to the good <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> whereof we are Inhabitants. Let the <hi>Health,</hi> the <hi>Growth,</hi> the <hi>Peace,</hi> the <hi>Plenty</hi> and the <hi>Protection</hi> of our <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> procure our Acknowledgments unto our God.</p>
            <p>And ſo coming to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e of a ſhort <hi>Winter-Day,</hi> ſpent in ſuch Devotions, as will a little Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble and Antedate the Heavenly Exerciſes of our Long <hi>Eternity,</hi> ſet us break off with a few Ingenuous Thoughts upon that Enquiry of a Thankful Soul. <hi>What ſhall I Render to the Lord for all His Benefits?</hi> Or, <hi>What Special Service is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40620:40"/>there that I may Do for the God, whoſe Goodneſs and Mercy has followed me all my Dayes?</hi> Contrive, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and Execute accordingly. Behold, A <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Day</hi> well ſpent.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. However it may be, as to the <hi>Works</hi> of our <hi>Particular Calling,</hi> yet as to the <hi>Works</hi> of our GENERAL CALLING, we ſhould not let the <hi>Winter</hi> be our <hi>Hindrance.</hi> Altho' we have a <hi>Seal'd Hand,</hi> as to our <hi>Temporal</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in the <hi>Winter,</hi> yet let us not then <hi>Deal with a ſlack Hand,</hi> as to our <hi>Spiritual.</hi> The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is a <hi>Work</hi> that we have to do, in the <hi>Winter</hi> as well as in the <hi>Summer;</hi> and it is the <hi>Work of God. Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation-work,</hi> is to be no ſmall ſhare of our <hi>Winter-work.</hi> Our <hi>Winter</hi> Prayers muſt not be, our <hi>Coldeſt</hi> ones, tho' 'tis in a Cold Air that we make them. Our Cares to make our <hi>Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Election ſure,</hi> are not excuſed by the <hi>Winter; That</hi> muſt not cool them. Tho' the work of Laying in for the <hi>Winter,</hi> be over with us; yet the work of Laying in for <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is not over; that is to be done all the <hi>Winter Long.</hi> The <hi>Word</hi> of God, that is to be <hi>Read,</hi> and to be <hi>Heard,</hi> as well as <hi>Obey'd,</hi> now no Leſs than formerly. The Pſalmiſt has joyned thoſe things, <hi>The Lord gives the Snow, the Froſt, the Ice,</hi> and, <hi>Hee ſhewed His Word unto Jacob.</hi> Truly, the <hi>Snow,</hi> the <hi>Froſt,</hi> the <hi>Ice,</hi> may not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from the minding of that <hi>Word.</hi> There is the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>Watching</hi> and <hi>Fighting</hi> againſt our Inviſible Adverſaries; and this is to be done as much in the <hi>Winter,</hi> as at any Time whatever. Other <hi>Wars</hi> are ordinarily intermitted in the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40620:41"/>by the <hi>Armies</hi> then retiring to their <hi>Winter Quarters.</hi> But the <hi>Winter</hi> gives no Intermiſſion unto theſe <hi>Wars of the Lord.</hi> In one of the Pſalms, we read, <hi>The Dragons,</hi> joyned with the <hi>Hall, and the Snow, and the Vapour</hi> whereof theſe are compoſed. Why, when the <hi>Vapours</hi> of the <hi>Winter</hi> are about our Ears, we ſhall ſtill have, <hi>The Dragons,</hi> alſo to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ict withal. Tho' our other <hi>Sna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> do all the <hi>Winter</hi> Ly Idle in their Holes, yet the <hi>Old Serpent,</hi> is as buſy then as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and we ſhould then be as vigilant againſt the <hi>Spirits,</hi> who go about <hi>Seeking whom they may Devour.</hi> God make us, like the Valiant <hi>Benajah,</hi> who <hi>ſlew a Lion in a Pit in a Snowy Day!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is our <hi>work.</hi> But now for the Obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this <hi>work</hi> in the <hi>Winter,</hi> there is a frequent Abuſe of that Scripture, in Mat. 9.12. <hi>I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice.</hi> The <hi>Deceitful Hearts</hi> of Men pretend the Duties of <hi>Mercy,</hi> to Plunge themſelves into the moſt horrible Inſtances of <hi>Cruelty;</hi> I mean, they make themſelves a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to the ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icle Juſtice and Vengeance of God. But I ſay, <hi>Go ye, and Learn what that meaneth!</hi> It is true, That <hi>Mercy</hi> to our ſelves, may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt the CIRCUMSTANCES of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or, the <hi>Exte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iours,</hi> in the AFFIRMATIVES of Religion. It is not <hi>pleaſing</hi> to God, that we ſhould be really <hi>Cruel</hi> to our ſelves. <hi>Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> do not commonly oblige us to overthrow the Health of our <hi>own Bodies.</hi> We cannot be <hi>Righteous</hi> at all, except we <hi>Deny</hi> our ſelves; but when we come to <hi>Deſtroy</hi> our ſelves, by Exceſſes in the <hi>Manner of Doing,</hi> what muſt be <hi>Done,</hi> tho
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40620:41"/>we ſhould be <hi>Deſtroy'd</hi> for it, then we become <hi>Righteous Overmuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, Firſt, Let us keep cloſe to this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;</hi> Tho' <hi>poſitive</hi> Commandments may be ſome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imes Invaded for the ſake of <hi>Mercy,</hi> yet <hi>Negative</hi> Commandments may never be ſo. When we may do <hi>Leſs</hi> of that which is <hi>Good,</hi> yet we may do <hi>Nothing</hi> of what is <hi>Ill.</hi> And then, Let us keep this <hi>Diſtinction;</hi> There is a Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Ungrateful Abatements,</hi> and <hi>Well-pleaſing O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions</hi> of our Devotions on the ſcore of <hi>Mercy</hi> pretended for. 'Tis one thing for us, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d againſt our Choice, unto the Diminution of our <hi>Deſired</hi> and <hi>Uſual</hi> Meaſure, in our pious P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nces; and another, our Gladly accepting of an <hi>Occaſion,</hi> that we hope, will ſet us at <hi>Liberty,</hi> from doing any thing at all.</p>
            <p>It is complained, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.4. <hi>The Sluggard will not Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh by reaſon of the Cold;</hi> or, of the <hi>Winter.</hi> Gods <hi>Cold</hi> is oftentimes made an Excuſe for our <hi>Sin.</hi> Even ſo, The <hi>ſluggiſh</hi> Hearts of men, will neglect thoſe Exerciſes of <hi>Piety,</hi> wherein we <hi>Plough</hi> for our Everlaſting Welfare. Why ſo? Truly, 'tis the <hi>Cold</hi> of the <hi>Winter</hi> that hinders them. We read concerning <hi>Peter,</hi> that he was by the <hi>Cold</hi> hurried into the way of <hi>Temptation.</hi> It is ſaid, in Joh. 18.18. <hi>They made a Fire of Coals, for it was Cold; and</hi> Peter <hi>ſtood and warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf:</hi> and you know what follow'd! Now, 'tis by the <hi>Cold</hi> that we are often burried into the way of <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> too. As he <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny'd</hi> his Lord, partly thro' the Snares of the <hi>Cold;</hi> ſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40620:42"/>we often <hi>Forget</hi> our Lord, becauſe the <hi>Cold</hi> makes us be where we ſhould not be. They are not only thoſe who fly to the <hi>Tavern</hi> in the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and who there do poyſon their Souls with <hi>Drinking,</hi> with <hi>Bad Company,</hi> with <hi>Fooliſh Talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> by the <hi>Fireſide,</hi> that Sin by <hi>reaſon of the Cold;</hi> but it is alſo the fault of thoſe, who by <hi>reaſon of the Cold,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not viſit their own Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets, or the Aſſembli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Good Men, or the Worſhip of God, as much as they can. If you think it enough, to ſtay at Home, on a Winter Day, and, as you ſay, Read a <hi>Chapter in Job, I</hi> pray, Let it be that <hi>Chapter,</hi> where <hi>Job</hi> is told, That the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God, the <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of His Word, muſt be duely conſidered and conſulted by thoſe that would <hi>be delivered from going down to the Pit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVell, But now, Let us by a ſacred <hi>Antipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſteſis</hi> take more pains for the Serving of God, in the <hi>VVinter,</hi> than we did in the more Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seaſons of the Year. Yea, and Let us do it with an Expectation, That the more <hi>Pains</hi> we take to attend the Service of God, the more will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Requite our <hi>Pains</hi> with ſuch Incomes of <hi>Grace</hi> and perhaps of <hi>Joy,</hi> into our Souls, as will be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the <hi>Merchandiſe of Silver,</hi> or the <hi>Gain of the fineſt Gold.</hi> The Apoſtle ſpeaking of what he had Endured in Serving of God, ſays in 2 Cor. 11.27. <hi>I have been in Cold, and Nakedneſs.</hi> It is Likely that he refers, to what is Reported, in Acts 28.2. That they were Shipwrack'd upon <hi>Malta,</hi> and there, <hi>The Barbarous People ſhew'd them no Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40620:42"/>Kindneſs, and kindled a Fire, and Received them, becauſe of the Cold.</hi> Yea, but our God, ordinarily calls none of us to Endure a <hi>Cold,</hi> ſo extreamly circumſtanced. We are to know, That we are now in a State of <hi>Probation,</hi> as to our <hi>Bodies:</hi> if we now put our <hi>Bodies</hi> to neceſſary <hi>Trouble,</hi> in the Serving of God, and if now in our <hi>Bodies,</hi> we <hi>Endure Hardneſs, as Good Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> we ſhall be Rewarded in the <hi>Glory</hi> of theſe <hi>Bodies,</hi> at the <hi>Reſurrection of the Juſt.</hi> For every pinch of <hi>Cold,</hi> whereto we have Expoſed our <hi>Bodies,</hi> in the Serving of God, all the <hi>Winter</hi> Long, we ſhall be Recompenced in our Glorify'd <hi>Bodies,</hi> when, <hi>The Times of a Refreſhing Coolneſs ſhall come, by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord.</hi> Wherefore, now Let us do the <hi>more</hi> Works of PIETY, rather than the <hi>Fewer,</hi> for the <hi>Cold</hi> of our <hi>Winter.</hi> It is noted concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Time of our Lords Coming up to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of God, in Joh. 10.22, 23. <hi>It was the Feaſt of the Dedication, and it was Winter; And Jeſus walked in the Temple.</hi> It may be that <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet given up your ſelves unto the Bleſſed God, with ſo Explicit a <hi>Dedication,</hi> as would be a no leſs <hi>Comfortable,</hi> than <hi>Reaſonable Service.</hi> Then do it this <hi>Winter;</hi> while you have ſo much Time to <hi>Dedicate</hi> unto ſuch a <hi>Service.</hi> But having ſo done, Be ſure to come up unto the <hi>Temple,</hi> in the <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> as much as ever you can. Poſſibly, you have never yet come into any Evangelical CHURCH-FELLOWSHIP, according to the Precept of the Holy JESUS; No, you are ſo far from <hi>Walking</hi> with Him, in the <hi>Temple,</hi> that you never yet En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40620:43"/>into His <hi>Temple,</hi> of Believers Aſſociated for the Deſigns of the Goſpel. I ſay then, LET THIS WORK BE DONE BEFORE THIS WINTER BE OUT. Having firſt Given your ſelves unto God in Chriſt, with <hi>Full purpoſe,</hi> To be <hi>for Him, and not for another,</hi> then Give your ſelves unto ſome Holy <hi>Society</hi> of His People, that Worſhip Him according to the Order of the Goſpel. I pray, Let the Lord <hi>this winter,</hi> ſee you in His TEMPLE.</p>
            <p>Yea, Whatever <hi>work</hi> we have to do for our Souls, Let not the <hi>VVinter</hi> give any <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> to our <hi>Working out of our own Salvation. Jacob</hi> thro the Love of <hi>Rachel,</hi> could Encounter more than a Little <hi>Winter,</hi> for more than One Seven Years together; ſaid he, in Gen. 31.40. <hi>In the Day the Drought, and the Froſt by Night conſumed me.</hi> The ſudden Changes from <hi>Heat</hi> unto <hi>Cold,</hi> like thoſe in our own Countrey, it ſeems did ſometime bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g <hi>Feavers</hi> and <hi>Agues</hi> upon the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch! But ſhall not we be willing to do as much for our own Souls? O patiently undergo a Little <hi>Froſt,</hi> for the ſake of their Deliverance, from the <hi>Outer Darkneſs,</hi> where there is <hi>Gnaſhing of Teeth,</hi> for ever! Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, has Embalmed the Memory of ſeveral <hi>Martyrs,</hi> who choſe the <hi>Fiery</hi> Anguiſh of being <hi>Frozen unto Death,</hi> rather than they would <hi>Sin</hi> againſt God, and incur the <hi>Fire</hi> of Damnation. Methinks, 'twould <hi>Fire</hi> the <hi>Coldeſt</hi> Heart imaginable, to read the Elegant Orations of the Eloquent Ancients, in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of thoſe Renowned <hi>Martyrs!</hi> And
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40620:43"/>ſhall <hi>we</hi> then think much ſometimes to feel our ſelves a little <hi>VVinteriſh,</hi> while we are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Things that muſt be done, for our Getting out of our <hi>Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and for our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with that Lord who <hi>Saves His People from their Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, Let us Get into our Hearts, an <hi>Heat</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> to God, that will carry us eaſily thro' all the <hi>Cold</hi> of the <hi>VVinter</hi> in the Serv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God. Of <hi>Love,</hi> 'tis ſaid, in Cant. 8.7. <hi>Many waters cannot quench Love, neither can the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds drown it.</hi> Of this <hi>Love,</hi> I may ſay, <hi>Many VVinters cannot ſtarve it, neither can the Froſt Nip it.</hi> Said the Apoſtle, <hi>The Love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth us.</hi> Altho' they that would ſuitably Serve God in the <hi>winter,</hi> muſt meet with many Difficulties; yet if we had this <hi>Love</hi> in us, that would <hi>Conſtrain</hi> us, to Go <hi>Freely</hi> through them all.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. There are many <hi>works</hi> of CHARITY, whereto the Rigours and Horrors of a <hi>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p winter,</hi> may <hi>ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pen</hi> our Inclinations; and we ſhould then <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lly Demonſtrate</hi> our being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Inclined. There are thoſe which are Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically called, GOOD WORKS; altho' we have a <hi>Seal'd Hand</hi> in the <hi>winter,</hi> yet we ſhould not then have a <hi>cloſe Fiſt,</hi> for ſuch <hi>works</hi> as thoſe. To Relieve and Support the <hi>Poor,</hi> is the <hi>work of God;</hi> and Let us now <hi>Know,</hi> what it is to <hi>Do,</hi> as much as we can of that <hi>work.</hi> The charitable <hi>Job,</hi> could ſay, in chap. 30.24. <hi>VVas not my
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40620:44"/>Soul grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d for the Poor?</hi> Why, Altho' we have an <hi>bundance of all things</hi> about us, yet our <hi>winters</hi> are very pinching and piercing Things unto us; well, but now Let us think on the <hi>Poor,</hi> that ſit ſhiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over a <hi>VVidows Fire!</hi> that are but thin clad, and worſe Fed, and have thoſe two Powerful Things, <hi>VVinter</hi> and <hi>Poverty,</hi> at once falling, like <hi>Armed men</hi> upon them. O think on theſe <hi>Poor</hi> Ones, till our <hi>Souls</hi> are duely <hi>Grieved</hi> for them. Let not our <hi>Charity</hi> be as <hi>Cold</hi> as the <hi>winter;</hi> and Let none of us contribute unto the fulfilling of that Prophecy, in Mat. 24.12. <hi>The Love of many ſhall wax cold.</hi> Yea, ſuppoſe our <hi>Charity</hi> were as <hi>cold</hi> as the <hi>water,</hi> yet Let it be like the <hi>water</hi> for this one thing more; the <hi>water</hi> in the <hi>winter</hi> will Expend and Extend it ſelf unto almoſt an <hi>Eighth part</hi> of the Space it poſſeſſed before; and this with ſuch a Force, as to Burſt the very Subſtance of even <hi>Metalline Veſſels,</hi> which would have kept it in. May nothing now Obſtruct ſuch a <hi>Spread</hi> of our <hi>Charity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is mentioned, as the Lamentable Condition of ſome, in <hi>Job</hi> 14.7. <hi>They have no Covering in the Cold.</hi> I beſeech you, Let our Liberality <hi>Cover</hi> thoſe that are ſo miſerable: and therefore Let us <hi>Deviſe Liberal Things.</hi> But now I ſpeak of ſuch <hi>Deviſing,</hi> there is one charitable propoſal, which you ſhall permit me to urge upon you. 'Tis this, <hi>VVhen winter is coming on, &amp; our winter-ſtock of Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries is Laying in, Let us then ſeriouſly conſider with our ſelves,</hi> Who of my Neighbours are there that want my Charity? <hi>&amp; Let us LIBERALLY divide among,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40620:44"/>them fit Proportions of the ſame Stores, that we Lay up for our ſelves; or otherwiſe Enable them to Lay up ſomething of the Like Stores for their Sucour in the Neceſſities of the Advancing VVinter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I am ſure of; that all our <hi>Accommodations</hi> all the <hi>winter</hi> long, will be very much the <hi>Sweeter,</hi> if not alſo the <hi>Surer,</hi> unto us, for our having firſt Liberally Imparted a <hi>Share</hi> unto our Honeſt Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that were altogether Deſtitute of ſuch <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations.</hi> We read, <hi>in a certain place,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>The Treaſures of Snow.</hi> One of the Ancients does expound thoſe <hi>Treaſures</hi> to be, <hi>Worldly Riches</hi> which the next Shower of Calamity will waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, like a <hi>Snow-Drift,</hi> and leave only ſome <hi>dirt,</hi> behind in the owners heart. Why, if we would not have our <hi>Treaſures,</hi> to melt, and waſt, like thoſe of the <hi>Snow,</hi> employ thoſe <hi>Treaſures</hi> for the Conſolation, of the miſerable, whoſe miſeries are encreaſed by the <hi>Snow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CHRISTIANS, If you anſwer your <hi>Worthy Name,</hi> both the Word of CHRIST and the Day of CHRIST, find awful Reſentments with you. Well then; You are in that <hi>Word</hi> Informed, and Aſſured, with what Glories in that <hi>Day,</hi> all your GOOD WORKS will be acknowledged. This <hi>Winter,</hi> feed a Starving Neighbour, and a ſenſible Jeſus will then ſay, <hi>I am feaſted.</hi> And the effect of it will be, that he will invite you to the <hi>Fat things of His Houſe,</hi> yea, to the Delicious <hi>Feaſt,</hi> which he has in His <hi>Eternal Mountain.</hi> Again, This <hi>Winter</hi> Lodge an Harbourleſs Neighbour, and a ſenſible Jeſus will ſay, <hi>I am entertained.</hi> You will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40620:45"/>like ſome, <hi>Entertain Angels unawares,</hi> but, <hi>The Lord of Angels,</hi> Himſelf. Further, This <hi>Winter</hi> clothe a Naked Neighbour, and a ſenſible Jeſus will ſay, <hi>I have Robes put upon me.</hi> 'Twil he as if you had Adorned the <hi>Temples</hi> of God. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, This <hi>Winter</hi> Comfort a Sick Neighbour, and a ſenſible Jeſus will ſay, <hi>'Tis I that am Refreſhed.</hi> So, you that have <hi>Conſidered the Poor</hi> ſhall have your own <hi>Beds turned</hi> by the Lord for you, in your own <hi>Sickneſs.</hi> Finally, This <hi>Winter,</hi> come to a Neighbour in <hi>Priſon,</hi> and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l come to a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Jeſus there. What you do for the <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Captives, will be done to the Great <hi>Lord-Redtemer.</hi> They are the worſt of <hi>Miſers,</hi> whom ſuch <hi>Motives,</hi> will not we ſwade unto ſomewhat of <hi>Liberality!</hi> But behold, the <hi>Winter</hi> it ſelf alſo comes in as one of our <hi>Motives.</hi> The wiſe man ſaid in Eccl. 11 2. <hi>Give a portion to ſeven, and alſo to eight, for thou knoweſt not, what evil ſhall be upon the Earth.</hi> Yea, but now the <hi>winter,</hi> is coming, we do know much of the <hi>Evil</hi> that will then be <hi>upon the Earth,</hi> and let us therefore give a <hi>portion</hi> of our Supplies unto as many as we can.</p>
            <p>It would be a ſad thing, if we ſhould in the <hi>winter</hi> be driven out of our Habitations. Our Lord has allow'd us to deprecate very heartily, <hi>A flight from our Houſes in the winter:</hi> and for the ſame cauſe, <hi>A fire on our houſes in the winter,</hi> deſerves as warm a Deprecation. Well, the way for us to preſerve our <hi>Houſes,</hi> is to make <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da's</hi> of them, that is <hi>Houſes of Mercy,</hi> to the poor.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40620:45"/>Let <hi>our Houſes, be Alms-Houſes,</hi> and we may hope, that inaſmuch as we thus <hi>Fear God,</hi> He will neither <hi>Cut off our dwellings,</hi> nor <hi>Cut off</hi> us from <hi>our dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Olaus Magnus</hi> admires the Lake, near the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Norway,</hi> whoſe veins of <hi>Sulphur</hi> under it, keep it from any Congelation in the Coldeſt Winter of that Northern Climate: may the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of that Lake, be emulated, by the perpetual <hi>warmth</hi> of our Charity.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. And now to have done; Let the <hi>Cold</hi> of the <hi>winter,</hi> very powerfully <hi>warm</hi> our hearts to ſhake of that SINFUL COLD, which has gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon our Hearts. To Recover any <hi>Frozen part</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> with ſafety, the way is to Rub it with <hi>Snow.</hi> Give me leave now to rub ſomewhat of the <hi>winter</hi> upon you, for the Recovery of your <hi>Frozen Souls.</hi> Indeed, There is a <hi>Coolneſs of Spirit,</hi> which would be the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of the man that has it. So we read in Prov. 17.27. <hi>A man of underſtanding is of an Excellent Spirit:</hi> ſome read it, <hi>Of a Cool Spirit.</hi> It would indeed render us, <hi>The excellent in the earth,</hi> to have a <hi>Spirit</hi> free from thoſe Heats which the moſt of men, are by provocations thrown into. A <hi>Cool Spirit,</hi> is a <hi>meek Spirit;</hi> and we ſhould Labour for ſuch a Spirit, not only under <hi>Afflictions</hi> from the Hand of <hi>God,</hi> but under <hi>Injuries</hi> from the Hand of <hi>Man</hi> alſo. Of ſuch a <hi>Cool Spirit,</hi> was the Great <hi>Moſes</hi> generally under all the Murmurings, the Reproaches, and the Froward Humours of his Congregation; and of ſuch a <hi>Spirit,</hi> I am to tell you, <hi>Tis in the ſight of God, of great Price.</hi> But then, There is a <hi>Coldneſs of Spirit,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:40620:46"/>againſt which we ſhould be always <hi>Awake;</hi> and particularly, in the <hi>Cold</hi> of the <hi>winter</hi> be Awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>FIRST, There is the <hi>Cold</hi> of our FORMALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY, againſt which we ſhould now fortify our Souls. <hi>Formality,</hi> lies in much <hi>Cold</hi> mixed with ſome <hi>Warmth;</hi> it lies in ſome Kindneſs for the <hi>Thing that Good it,</hi> over born with predominant Regards unto the world. This <hi>Lukewarmneſs,</hi> is that Abominable Indifferency about, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> whereat our Lord ſays of them that have it, <hi>I will ſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them out of my mouth.</hi> But it is Required in Rom. 12.11. <hi>Be Fervent in Spirit ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord:</hi> It may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endred, <hi>Be Boiling Hot, in it.</hi> There are ſome <hi>VVell</hi> that <hi>Boil</hi> all the year about, and that ſeem rather <hi>Hotter</hi> in the <hi>winter</hi> than in the reſt of the year. Even ſo ſhould it be with us, as to that principle within us, which is, <hi>A well of water ſpringing up to Everlaſting Life.</hi> There is a <hi>Zeal,</hi> wherewith we ſhould purſue all our Everlaſting Intereſts; and as the <hi>Fire</hi> burns fierceſt in the <hi>winter,</hi> ſo the <hi>Cold</hi> of the <hi>winter</hi> ſhould be but adding <hi>fire</hi> unto our <hi>Zeal.</hi> Our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Occupations are interrupted by the <hi>winter;</hi> yea, but let us now, be more Lively than ever, in our Spiritual <hi>Husbandry,</hi> and in <hi>Ploughing up the Fallow Ground of our Hearts.</hi> Let us now be more Lively than ever, in our Spiritual <hi>Merchandiſe,</hi> and in Bartering for the <hi>Pearl of Great Price.</hi> Let us now, be more lively than ever, in our Spritual <hi>Building;</hi> euen, in <hi>Building up</hi> ourſelves, &amp; one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in <hi>our moſt Holy Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:40620:46"/>
            <p>'Tis true, we have <hi>Hearts,</hi> that are as <hi>Cold as a Stone,</hi> when they ſhould be concerned about the Things of another World; yet there is a way to help it: Let us Cry to our God, who ſays, in Ezek 36.26, 27. <hi>I will take away the Heart of Stone; yet for this I will be Enquired of, to do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, SECONDLY, There is the <hi>Cold</hi> of our UNREGENERACY to be reſcued where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, the Deſires, the Wiſhes of our Souls are to be exceeding <hi>Ardent.</hi> In the Travels of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we read much about, <hi>The Wilderneſs of Sin;</hi> which is in Engliſh, <hi>The Wilderneſs of Cold.</hi> Why, to ſpeak nothing but <hi>Engliſh,</hi> All you that are in, <hi>The Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of Sin,</hi> are in a <hi>Cold Wilderneſs</hi> indeed; a <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> of Deadly, yea, of Damning, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las!</hi> for you, that you don't yet count it, <hi>Inſuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cold!</hi> It was the Gladſome Song, in Can. 2.11. <hi>Lo, The Winter is paſt, the Rain is over and gone.</hi> What is that <hi>Winter?</hi> It has been Interpreted for the, <hi>Tempus praecedens Vocationem;</hi> the Time while we are yet in our <hi>Unregeneracy.</hi> O that all you, with whom it is yet ſuch a Time, of <hi>Winter,</hi> might before this <hi>winter</hi> be out, be able to Sing, <hi>The Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my Unbelief is paſt, my Sin is over and gone!</hi> The Excellent <hi>Bartholinus</hi> hath remarked it; That the <hi>Bodies</hi> of them who are kill'd in the <hi>Winter,</hi> uſe to be found, in juſt the ſame <hi>Features,</hi> and <hi>Poſtures,</hi> that were upon them, when they Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their mortal Wounds: they are found Gap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Staring, Frowning, and with their Hands Extended, juſt as they were in their fatal Fall. Truly, ſo, if you Dy in this <hi>Winter</hi> of your <hi>Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:40620:47"/>thoſe Impreſſions of <hi>Sin</hi> upon your <hi>Spirits,</hi> wherein you Dy, will become Eternally Indelible and Unalterable. You'l be as it were Irrecovera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Congeled into ſuch an Ungodly <hi>Temper,</hi> as that wherein you do Expire; Incurable will be your <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ipathy</hi> to God, and your Prejudice againſt all that is <hi>Holy, and Juſt and Good.</hi> So, Intermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orments and Regrets, will become in ſome ſort <hi>Eſſential</hi> to your to ſaken Souls; and you will be <hi>Confirmed</hi> in the Natural Conſequents of Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God, world without End; where the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty—<hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibet, mirabile dictu,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Aeternam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ammis Glaciem, Aeternoque Rigore</l>
                  <l>Ardentes horrent Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>puli.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>[What <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius</hi> writes about the Top of Burning <hi>Aetna.</hi>] Would it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be a moſt Irkſome Thing to have a perpetual <hi>Winter</hi> upon us? But let all <hi>Unregenerates</hi> know, That it is always <hi>winter</hi> with them. Conſider Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Conſider whether you have not the ſigns of the worſt <hi>winter,</hi> in the World upon you. The Cold of the <hi>winter</hi> does make things to become <hi>Unactive</hi> As <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and the like Inſtruments will not Go in the <hi>winter;</hi> even the very Metal of them ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>metimes is thereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſo that their Teeth loſe their Congruity; thus the <hi>Owners</hi> are ſufficiently Liſtleſs too. And are not <hi>you</hi> ſo? You can't <hi>Come,</hi> no, nor ſo much as <hi>Look,</hi> to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, for <hi>Life,</hi> tho' the Life of your Souls depend upon it. You can't <hi>Walk</hi> with God, or <hi>Move</hi> with any Activity, much leſs, can you <hi>Run</hi> with an <hi>Enlarged Heart</hi> in the <hi>Way of His Commandments.</hi> Again, The Cold of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40620:47"/>the <hi>winter</hi> does make things to become <hi>Inſenſible.</hi> They who Dy of the Gold, after their <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> are throughly ſiezed, often grow paſt feeling; and fall into a <hi>Lethargie Drowſineſs,</hi> wherein and whereof they are like to Dy Irrecoverably. And are not <hi>you</hi> ſo? You don't <hi>Hear,</hi> the Calls of the Goſpel, tho' the Loudeſt <hi>Thunders,</hi> are not ſo loud as the voice of that <hi>Silver-Trumpet.</hi> You don't <hi>See</hi> the <hi>Beauty</hi> of you S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar, tho' He be <hi>Altogether Lovely.</hi> You don't <hi>fed</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oad of your Sins, tho' that Infinite Load, be heavier than Talents, and Mount<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins of Lead upon your Souls: Is there not a <hi>Dead Sleep</hi> upon yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? Once more, The Cold of the <hi>winter</hi> brings <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trefaction</hi> with it. Tho' whilſt Bodies continue Frozen, the <hi>Cold</hi> by arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Particles, from whoſe Tumultuary Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Corruption uſes to proceed, may keep the Ill Operations of the <hi>Cold</hi> upon the violated Textures of Bodies, from appearing; ſo Dead Bodies in <hi>Greenland</hi> have been preſerved thirty years entire from Rottenneſs; yet when once that is remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they commonly and ſpeedily diſcover how much their Texture had been vitiated by the Cold. And, are <hi>you</hi> Free from That? Why then have you ſuch <hi>Rotten Communications?</hi> and ſuch <hi>Rotten Imaginations?</hi> Why are you ſo much like <hi>Open Sepulchres?</hi> And now what mean you, ye Unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerates, that you are not yet weary of this wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>winter?</hi> Even ſolid <hi>Marbles</hi> have ſometimes bin broken by the <hi>Cold;</hi> O let it break thy Rocky Heart, when thou thinkeſt of the <hi>Cold,</hi> wherein it is <hi>Bewintered.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:40620:48"/>
            <p>It was the Occaſional Reflection of a <hi>Young Diſciple,</hi> in a bitter cold Morning.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <bibl>[See the Life of my Brother, <hi>Nath. Mather,</hi> p. 40]</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jan.</hi> 8. Being about to Riſe, I felt the <hi>Cold</hi> in a manner Extraordinary; which inclined me to ſeek more <hi>warmth</hi> in my Bed" before I Roſe: But ſo extream was the <hi>Cold,</hi> that this was not feaſible, whereupon I Reſolved to <hi>Dreſs</hi> my ſelf without any more ado, and ſo going to the <hi>Fire</hi> in my Clothes, I ſoon became warm enough. Turn this, O <hi>my Soul,</hi> into an uſeful Meditation. There is a Neceſſity of my Riſing out of my <hi>Bed,</hi> the Bed of <hi>Security,</hi> which I am under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of; and to <hi>Live</hi> unto Chriſt, and <hi>walk in the Light.</hi> In order hereunto, I muſt <hi>put on</hi> my Soul, the <hi>Garments,</hi> which are to be had from the Lord Jeſus. Now, to Awaken me out of my <hi>Sleep,</hi> &amp; my <hi>Security,</hi> I am to ſet before me the <hi>Sun;</hi> the Goſpel of, <hi>The Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> doth Enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en my mind, and tell me, that I was before, mufled up in <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and that if I continued therein, I ſhould <hi>ſtarve</hi> and periſh. I am alſo taught" That when men are <hi>Convinced</hi> of their miſerable Condition, they will rather Endeavour to Eaſe and Comfort and Cheriſh themſelves, by ſomething in <hi>Themſelves,</hi> than put on the <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Garments,</hi> which the Lord Jeſus Chriſt has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vsded for them. An Evil to be, by me Avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!</p>
            </q>
            <p>O that all our <hi>Young</hi> Ones, would argue at ſuch a rate. You think of putting off your <hi>Converſion,</hi> till <hi>Old Age.</hi> Fond Souls: Beſides the horrible
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40620:48"/>Danger, wherein you are, of being like thoſe <hi>Who Dy in Youth, becauſe their Life is among the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean:</hi> This were juſt as if you ſhould put off, all the Buſineſs of the <hi>Summer,</hi> until the Depth of <hi>Winter.</hi> Say now, in the midſt of <hi>winter,</hi> ſay, vain Youths, whether you could ſubſiſt, if you had no <hi>Bread"</hi> but what this <hi>Winter</hi> were now to be Sow'd or Planted; and no <hi>Money,</hi> but what were now to be Laboured or? It muſt be nothing but, <hi>A Madneſs in the Heart,</hi> that can encourage you, to Delay your Converſion, till the <hi>Winter</hi> of <hi>Old Age</hi> do overtake you. O do not ſo play the <hi>Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper;</hi> but hear Counſil, and, <hi>Go to the Ant thou Sluggard!</hi> For perſons to be <hi>Cold,</hi> Key-cold, yea, Death cold, about the matters of their Souls, while they are in their <hi>Youth,</hi> and think that they will uſe more <hi>warm</hi> Endeavours about thoſe matters in their <hi>Age;</hi> This truly, is a far odder thing than the Quality of that Fountain of <hi>Debris.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Frigore qui noctis fervet Calefactus &amp; Umbris,</l>
               <l>At Solis friget Radiſs Glacialis et Igoi.</l>
            </q>
            <p>'Tis <hi>Cold</hi> at High Noon, &amp; <hi>Warm</hi> at Midnight.</p>
            <p>And then, ſure they that are already come to <hi>Old Age,</hi> had need make ſure of <hi>Converſion,</hi> before it become altogether too late, hopeleſs, helpleſs, &amp; unattainable. My Fathers, you are now got into the <hi>winter</hi> of your Lives; Old Age begins to <hi>Snow</hi> upon your heads; &amp; your whole face, is that of the earth in <hi>winter.</hi> The Jews generally interr'd their <hi>Dead</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and <hi>Oak:</hi> [ſee 1 Sam. 31.13.] pleaſed perhaps with ſome ſuch parallel as this; that as the <hi>Tree</hi> ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>dead</hi> in the <hi>winter,</hi> had every Spring an Annual
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40620:49"/>and Notable <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> ſo the Dry <hi>Bones</hi> of men, ſhall have a new Sap of <hi>Life</hi> infuſed into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, at the Day of Judgment. Indeed, you that are under the Decays of Age, are like the <hi>Tree</hi> caſting of its Leaves in Autumn, every thing is now apace <hi>dying</hi> with you every day; you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l wither, till your being ſunk into the ground make it a perfect <hi>winter</hi> with you. You ſhall have a <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> but O tis high Time for you, to gain a good Aſſurance, that it ſhall be, <hi>The Reſurrection of Life,</hi> and not, <hi>The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Damnation;</hi> in a word, That nothing may ſucced, but <hi>An Eternal Spring.</hi> The Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſaid, <hi>Before Old Age, my care was to Live well; but now under Old Age, my care is to Dy well.</hi> Truly, Now <hi>winter</hi> is come, you have nothing elſe to take any <hi>Care</hi> about. If you have not in all this while, Secured a Saving Intereſt in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, or if you are not yet <hi>Purged from your old Sins,</hi> moſt horrid and monſtrous has been your <hi>Impenitency!</hi> And yet I am to tell you a very Glorious Thing; That Intereſt may ſtill be Secured. There was once a pretty <hi>Old man</hi> in ſome Diſtreſs, and it is ſaid, in Joh. 5 6. <hi>Jeſus kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w he had been a Long Time Ill, and ſaid unto him, W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t thou be made Whole?</hi> Even ſo, The Lord Jeſus Chriſt comes this Day, to you, <hi>Old men,</hi> that have been a <hi>Long Time</hi> in your Sins, and ſays, <hi>Old man, ſhall I yet be the Saviour of thy Soul?</hi> O then with Conquered and Conſenting Souls, now give your ſelves unto that Glorious Lord. But know, That if you do it not, before the <hi>winter</hi> of <hi>This Year,</hi> as well as of <hi>Your Age,</hi> be out, it will probably never be done at all. And then,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40620:49"/>alas, you will Expire, <hi>Accurſed like a Sinner of an Hundred Years Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto <hi>All,</hi> I ſay, God forbid, this <hi>winter</hi> ſhould paſs before you have made your <hi>Peace</hi> with Him. And, To Excite you hereunto; As in ſome Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Countreys, the Carpenters muſt <hi>Thaw</hi> their Wood, before they can <hi>Cut</hi> it; Let me aſſay to <hi>Thaw</hi> your Hearts, in order to a better ſhaping and ſquaring of them. I ſay then, Conſider that FIRE, as well as that <hi>Cold,</hi> which the Almighty God has to puniſh the Diſobedient. It has been ſaid, <hi>Who can ſtand before His Cold?</hi> But it has alſo been ſaid, <hi>Who can ſtand before His Fire?</hi> Thus, in Iſa. 33.14. <hi>Who among us can dwell with the Devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire? who among us ſhall dwell with Everlaſting Burnings?</hi> We wonder at the ſtrength of the <hi>Ice,</hi> when we ſee a piece of it, near three inches broad and a quarter of an inch thick, laid over a frame three inches diſtant, bear a weight of near twenty pounds, for a long while together: as Mr <hi>Boyl</hi> Experienced: or when we read <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, That their Septentrional <hi>Ice,</hi> is of ſuch a Tenacity, that when 'tis two or three fingers thick it will bear an Armed man upon it; &amp; when three or four Hands thick, vaſt Armies will venture over it, for their <hi>Winter-Wars.</hi> But thy Heart, O man, is prodigiouſly harder than a piece of <hi>Ice,</hi> if beſides the <hi>weight</hi> of Sin upon it, it can bear the Thought of the <hi>Fire that never ſhall be quenched.</hi> Remember, The Wrath of God, like a Formidable <hi>Fire,</hi> will at laſt, with Exquiſite Agonies, and Anguiſhes, Torture the Soul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them, that ſhall <hi>Dy</hi> in their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40620:50"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregeneracy</hi> One that felt ſome flaſhes of that <hi>Fire,</hi> in the Troubles of his Conſcience, hearing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſpeaking about, <hi>Burning to Death,</hi> cry'd out, <hi>O That is but a Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor to what I Endure!</hi> And another that was broiling in the <hi>Fire</hi> of ſuch Troubles, Roared in this manner, <hi>O might</hi> I <hi>have this mitigati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of my To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments, to dy as a Backlog in the Fire on the Hearth, for a thouſand Ages!</hi> Purge this: when you are by the <hi>Fire-ſide,</hi> this <hi>Winter,</hi> think ſeriouſly with your ſelves, <hi>Could I bear to R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ast in this Fire? Alas, This is but a pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Fire, to that wherein God will take vengeance on them that Know Him not, and that Obey not His Goſpel? And if I can't bear the Metaphor, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, not ſo much as for a minute, How then ſhall I bear to remain under the Wrath of God in Hell for infinitely more mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions of Ages, than a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Fires on Earth, have mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aſhes in the world!</hi> And O Let your Hearts be <hi>Thawed</hi> by ſuch Conſiderations, this <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> immediately to <hi>mourn</hi> for, and <hi>turn</hi> from all your Sins, and <hi>Give</hi> your ſelves to God in Chriſt, by a <hi>Covenant ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be Forgotten.</hi> It is a <hi>work</hi> of God, that is done <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> the <hi>winter</hi> is over, whereof there is mention, in Pſal: 104.30. <hi>Thou ſendeſt forth thy Spirit, and thou Renewest the Face of the Earth.</hi> O that ſuch a <hi>work</hi> as this may be done upon <hi>you, while</hi> this <hi>winter</hi> is running; <hi>Send forth thy Spirit, O m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Glorious Lord, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Renew the Hearts of them that have hitherto continued <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerates!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, I now Leave theſe my poor Labours, in the Hands of that Eternal <hi>Spirit,</hi> with my Humbleſt Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, That theſe my Endeavours, may be made Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and Acceptable unto His People, and aſſiſt my Neighbours in their Travels to that Countrey, where the <hi>Winter</hi> ſhall for ever <hi>Ceaſe from Troubling, and the VVeary be at Reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
